<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Boldly Goes</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 21:48:53 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 21:48:53 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trangia 28-T Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Inexpensive&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Light pans&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small form factor&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Heavy burner&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my mini Trangia 28-T for £18 from outdoorgear.co.uk in May 2016.  The neat stacking design, coupled with the low weight and price made the 28 stand out from the crowd straight away.  After dozens of overnighters and a few weekend trips I need to make some changes to save weight, but my cooking experience has been overwhelmingly positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pot, pot stand and frying pan are made from aluminium with the burner constructed from brass and the handle a lightweight alloy.  The aluminium construction means a slight drop in durability over some titanium counterparts, but the reduction in price and similar weight more than makes up for that in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aluminium pot is immediately recognisable as the design as featured in the larger Trangias which have become famous for standing up to all of the bumps and scrapes that occur in outdoor life.  I have seen several trodden on or sat on, bent completely out of shape, before being pushed back into a rough circle and chucked back on the fire.  Having used my mini pot on gas, alcohol and coals, I have no doubt that this smaller Trangia will stand up to the same punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frying pan is aluminium coated with non-stick coating which looks and feels quite fragile.  Trangia provide you with a sheet of thin plastic to protect the coating from the sharp edges of the pot stand and handle stored inside, this hasn’t stopped chipping where the pan clips over the lip of the pot.  Perhaps more of a design flaw than a quality issue, it is rather annoying and now it is chipped it will only get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burner, pot stand and handle are all solidly constructed; the burner and simmer ring fit together in a satisfyingly snug way; the handle, while flimsy, is actually surprisingly resilient and doesn’t buckle even when the pot is full of water; and the pot stand provides a rigid base for stirring and mixing over heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/handle.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Although it doesn&#39;t look like much, the handle is much easier to grip than the one in the Trangia 25 or 27.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first feature that stood out to me was the tiny form factor of the packed 28.  Everything fits neatly inside the systems pot with the frying pan over the top holding all of the components securely in place with room enough for teabags and 4 or 5 porridge packets to spare.  Being able to pick up one 15cm x 6.5cm item and know that you have packed your entire cookset in one go is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slimmed-down 0.8 litre pot of the mini coupled with the same brass burner as a larger Trangia leads to a much improved boil time, in my experience it takes around 6-7 minutes to boil 1 litre of water.  This reduced capacity has also allowed for a slimmer handle design which eliminates the chance of miss-gripping the pot rim and dropping it, which I used to do a lot with the old design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/overview.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some complain about the lack of a handle for the simmer ring, but you can slide it quite easily if you are careful and lift it slightly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only item which hasn’t changed in design from the larger Trangias is the burner itself.  It provides a stable temperature, doesn’t spit at all and the rubber-lined cap stops alcohol leaking through your backpack, but at 115g it makes up more than a third of the total weight.  I am definitely going to swap the burner out for a homemade coke can stove in the near future and probably leave the frying pan at home too which will reduce the weight to ~200g.  But if I’m changing the burner, leaving the pan (and lid) at home, why bother with the rest of it at all? Why not just buy a pot separately and make a stove to begin with? Well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market for alcohol stoves is limited.  It essentially boils down to Trangia burners, designs that look a lot like Trangia design knock offs, or simple stoves made from cans which seem expensive given that you could make them yourself for next to nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go ultralight straight away and have a tight-ish budget, I have only heard good things about  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.storminstovesystems.co.uk/&quot;&gt;stormin stove system&lt;/a&gt; at roughly £20 and 68g.  Paired with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alpkit.com/products/mytipot&quot;&gt;Mytipot&lt;/a&gt; which is £29 and weighs 94g and a homemade can stove you can achieve a system weighing just under 200g for £49.  But hold on, we already had this with the 28 if you leave the frying pan at home and swap out the stove, all for only £24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try a knock off Trangia design &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/NuoYa005-Solid-liquid-Alcohol-Cooking-Backpacking/dp/B00HBMOSJY/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/SZCXTOP-Portable-Alcohol-Aluminium-Backpacking/dp/B01N56JS2T/ref=sr_1_7?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-7&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Tatonka-Stainless-Steel-Alcohol-Burner-x/dp/B000G4XIA4/ref=sr_1_8?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-8&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;.
The ones I have seen weigh up to 100g more than the 28 burner and pot stand, and once you factor in the cost of a pot too they aren’t much cheaper, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, unless you make your own can stove, chicken wire pot stand, tinfoil wind guard and repurpose an aluminium mess tin as your pot, it’s going to be very hard indeed to find a system as light and functional as the 28-T for anywhere near the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/cooking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Whether you need to stop for a quick brew or cook a major meal for one or two, the 28-T can hack it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I opened my bottle of meths for my inaugural meal with the 28 I was struck with flashbacks to my scouting days.  Stuck on the side of a hill in darkness, three people around a Trangia 25, bodies positioned awkwardly in an attempt to shield the flame from the wind, hungry tempers flaring as pasta floating in a litre of water began to simmer lazily after more than 15 minutes of waiting.  I realised I may have made a huge mistake investing in another product from the same designers but a few meals in I realised most of my fears were misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For less money than a single titanium pot you get a complete, convenient, collapsible system.  Most of the components of the system are handy to have around to use on their own; the pot and handle do well on a gas stove, the stand and pot do well on their own with a different burner, the pot alone cooks on an open fire, the handle fits any pot with a lip.  It’s one of those kits that is so versatile at least one piece of it will end creeping its way into your pack wherever you are heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating 4/4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 28 makes for a brilliant starting stove for a new solo backpacker, and if you swap out some items it makes for a decent ultralight cookset for more experienced backpackers too.   All for less than the price of a single titanium cooking pot and a similar weight to many more expensive systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/trangia-28t-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/trangia-28t-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wisport Sparrow 20 Litre Backpack Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Endless versatility&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Durable&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Comfortable with any load&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Expensive for a 20L&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Heavy&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Sparrow from Military1st.co.uk in March 2016 for £60 after seeing it in use on the &lt;em&gt;AlfieAesthetics&lt;/em&gt; outdoor youtube channel.  I have used the Sparrow as a hybrid pack over the past year, loading up the outer straps with everything I need for a microadventure or weekend trip, then once I have made camp, using it as a day pack on short hikes.  Its impeccable build quality, versatile design and comfort have afforded me an enjoyable, more efficient hiking and camping experience with minimal drawbacks.  The standard Wisport 5 year warranty is the cherry the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/backpack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sparrow is made in Poland by Wisport, a Polish military and outdoor equipment company who supply the polish army among others.  This should tell you straight away that their gear, like most military equipment is going to be bomb proof, but that durability comes with a hefty weight cost.  The Sparrow is made from 500D Cordura, a splash resistant and generally tough fabric which will withstand everything but direct assault with a sharp knife.  This Cordura is held rigidly in place by faultless stitching which has remained rock steady through a year of frequent and quite harsh use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The straps, MOLLE webbing and mesh are all secured firmly; clearly intended to endure the tougher aspects of military life which means they are over engineered for civilian use.  The clips and buckles made by ITW Nexus and Duraflex haven’t lost their spring, and although I have been carrying heavy loads almost every time I have used the pack, show no signs of wear or fatigue.  The expansion connection points look quite flimsy at first but I have slung my 1.4kg sleeping bag from them numerous times with no problem at all.  The only quality issue I have had over 12 months is a frayed strap end, this was solved by resealing the end with a lighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/quality.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Rock solid zips, clips and buckles of the Sparrow inspire confidence even in the worst conditions.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;  Heavy loads can be slung under the pack using the flimsy looking but actually sturdy attachment points.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to fault the design of the Sparrow.  This pack is one which comes with all of the bells and whistles; hydration bladder support, clips for every occasion, straps to fasten all manner of sundries, attachment points for extra straps and standardised MOLLE webbing to attach any other military pockets or sheaths to the outside.  The Sparrow offers all of this while remaining comfortable even with all of these expansion options fully laden, and the option to attach a hip belt if it becomes to unwieldy.  It is a pack so versatile and so accommodating that you might end up packing too much for a microadventure even though it has only a ‘20 litre’ capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/straps.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The side straps of the Sparrow are the key feature, allowing you to carry loads which would be totally unrealistic with any other 20 litre pack.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of the Sparrow features two main pockets, one 5 litre front pocket contains a zipped mesh pocket for keys as well as clips for torches and carabiners.  I normally keep my Trangia, fuel and a bit of food in this pocket.  The 15 litre compartment features a flap to hold a hydration bladder and another zipped mesh pocket; after some gear Tetris there’s room enough for two litres of water, two days food and some well folded clothes.  The one issue when the pack is fully laden is waterproofing, while the Cordura does it’s best in the rain, anything more than a light shower will find its way into your precious sleeping socks straight away.  If you attach bulky items to the outside like me, you’ll want to pack a rain cover for a much larger backpack just in case, I chose a 65L which works well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/opening.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clips, flaps and pockets for all your small items; the fully hinged main compartment makes packing the larger pieces of gear easy too.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sparrow is tough to compare to other 20 litre backpacks, and other backpacks in general.  Generally day packs range from 15-25 litres and weigh 150-500 grams, but I can’t fit everything I can get into (or rather, onto) my Sparrow into a 35 litre Vango, let alone anything smaller.  If you want a more convenient day pack while still being able to go on weekend adventures for the same price as the Sparrow, you could get a, 68g &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.outdoorgb.com/p/Sea_to_Summit_20L_Ultra_Sil_Day_Pack/?utm_source=froogle&amp;amp;utm_medium=directory&amp;amp;utm_content=GBR&amp;amp;currency=GBP&amp;amp;country=GBR&amp;amp;SelectedBundle=184805&amp;amp;SelectedItem=687214&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjww7zHBRCToPSj_c_WjZIBEiQAj8il5K9p-2jg2PjfXTlZlzSqjOBCDi22Q0EWZoLt7aR6rAUaAv-k8P8HAQ&quot;&gt;Sea to Summit Ultra-Sil&lt;/a&gt; and a 45-65 litre  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shop-outdoors.co.uk/regatta-survivor-ii-45-litre-rucksack.html?fee=13&amp;amp;fep=15664&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjww7zHBRCToPSj_c_WjZIBEiQAj8il5KoITSfZ9I8zE1HZJY_2TbWFUY_fzQ57N4YKmhYZj9gaAvYA8P8HAQ&quot;&gt;Regatta&lt;/a&gt;.   This very reasonably priced duo will perform the same functions as the Sparrow while saving you about 90% of the weight during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nightgear.co.uk/en-UK/Snugpak-Xocet-35-Backpack/5150465ng.htm?colour=Black&amp;amp;size=One%20Size&quot;&gt;Snugpak Xocet&lt;/a&gt; is the most similar I have seen; most of the same straps and attachment points with the addition of some handy net pockets on the side for water bottles.  At £20 less than the Sparrow, only 30g more and with generally positive reviews, it’s a real contender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisport are currently introducing their Sparrow II range which sees some changes in the design to make it slightly less utilitarian, and brings the weight down by about 200g to 850g.  This makes it a much more appealing day pack option while retaining the majority of its straps and expandability options.  If mine breaks in 4 years after the warranty runs out (which I still see as being unlikely) the Sparrow II, or by then maybe III, will be my first choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t describe the Sparrow as luxurious, so maybe the it isn’t the Rolls Royce of 20 litre backpacks, but is a Range Rover; expensive, durable, heavy and lots storage options.  The designers thought of everything: attachment points, pockets and hydration bag options; expandability to the point that you will throw out all of your other backpacks below 55 litre capacity in disgust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/usage.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Being able to pack the same amount as with a 50+ litre bag without the bulk makes this my favourite microadventure bag.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the Sparrow is a brilliant challenge - I can fit my basic shelter on the outside, then I can just about fit my food, water and clothes on the inside.  It has inspired me to cut down unnecessary bulk from my setup and affords me a smug feeling when I see others with larger backpacks who have clearly overpacked for a short trip.  It is a bit of a bulky monster when used as a daypack, but when used in place of a 40-55L and separate 20L pack on a weekend adventure, suddenly all of it’s heavy attachments and over-engineered stitching make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-34&quot;&gt;Rating 3/4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need a rugged bushcraft, airsoft or hybrid weekend trip backpack, I would heartily recommend the Wisport Sparrow series.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/sparrow-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/sparrow-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alone in the Wilderness by Joseph Knowles</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt; is the memoir of Joseph Knowles, chronicling his 40 day stay in the woods in Maine which he undertook naked save a loincloth, without any survival equipment whatsoever.  An astonishing tale dotted with perilous encounters with bears and wildcats, Knowles breaks up his account with stories from his life and some of his musings on modern living in 1913.  As you continue through the book you might end up wondering whether the book isn’t all it seems to be…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thoughts on the book fluctuated as I began and finished the first third of the book.  I began bewildered and amazed by just how tough Knowles seemed to be even compared to the most extreme adventurers of that time.  I have read quite a few books from the turn of the century or before by adventurers and outdoorsmen who survived some truly amazing events.  Woolen garments, cast iron equipment, lacking nutrition and very basic or non-existent maps all made for what must have been a pretty hellish experience.  Knowles, though, seems to be a cut above them all; wandering into the forest &lt;em&gt;naked&lt;/em&gt; without so much as a knife with a plan to survive for 40 days, and all on the whim of a bet made in a bar.  That is a daunting task even for the most experienced bushcrafter when alone, it would surely be the test of his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/joseph.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Joseph Knowles photographed as he emerged from the forest, clothed in bear skin. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in the book Knowles writes of his experiences growing up in the forest in Maine near where he enters the woods to begin his task.  While giving no specifics, Knowles hints that some of the techniques he learned from his mother during childhood will help him to not just survive, but thrive in the wilderness during his stay.  His stories about his childhood certainly gave the impression that he has been tempered to endure this sort of test from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
“I didn&#39;t feel the hunger so keenly now, and as I walked along it came into my mind that I had heard that a man could go nine days without eating. Already I had been away from home three days. It would take two more to reach Wilton, which would leave four more before I actually starved to death, I figured.”
   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - Joseph Knowles&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He speaks of and approaches the whole adventure in a casual manner, spending the first few nights without fire, pacing to keep warm and not sleeping at all.  Fashioning shoes and trousers from bark with ease, he seems to find living in the woods as easy as living in a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read on, I did start to wonder whether some of the things he claimed to have done were actually physically possible.  I began to wonder whether even Ray Mears with a full support crew could dig a pit, trap a bear and beat it to death with just a tree limb in the space of four days with no tools.  Knowles continued that he had used his “bow and arrow” to shoot a large number of partridges without much effort at all.  This was when alarm bells really started ringing for me, it would surely take a fortnight if not more for an experienced bowyer to find and knapp flint for tools, make the tools, find suitable wood, fashion a bow, make the twine to string it, prepare the arrow shafts and heads, find feathers and fletch the arrows, let alone hunt and shoot accurately enough to kill a wild animal.  He had done all this on top of making several fires, a lean to shelter, clubbing a bear to death and spear fishing trout in his first two weeks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/moose.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Knowles left drawings and notes in several caches which were visited regularly by park rangers, these were his only contact with the outside world during his stay.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately turned to Google to find some answers and do some research on this bushcrafting superhero.  Sadly, from what I can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bostonmagazine.com/news/article/2013/03/26/naked-joe-knowles-nature-man-woods/&quot;&gt;find on the internet&lt;/a&gt;, it seems Joseph Knowles was at best a serial embellisher, and at worst (more likely) a con man out to make a quick buck, one of many making a dubious claim in a period when daring feats of endurance were all the rage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed reading &lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt;; even though I  learned the true story halfway through.  Knowles’ writing style definitely has that enticing twang of an old man whose tales probably feature fish twice their actual size, and there are some great (heavily inspired by Emerson) quotes and musings on being outdoors.  Ultimately, the unverifiable stories and questionable claims do mean that the story surrounding the inception of the idea and creation and release of the book are more interesting that the book itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
“As I made my way down to the spring early that morning I knew it was Sunday morning, and the thought came to me of how little churches would be needed if everyone knew and understood nature. Nature is, in truth, a religion in herself.”
   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - Joseph Knowles&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely recommend reading the incredible story of Joseph Knowles and the events surrounding the release of the book, but I’d recommend reading a version written by someone other than the man himself.  Really though, the book isn’t a bad read if you are still curious after that, the notes from Knowles’ friend, freelance writer Michael McKeogh, which apparently formed the basis of the story, did result in a well paced and eventful tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is for certain, he could definitely draw well with charcoal, even if it was from the comfort of a well furnished log cabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/doe.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt; is available for free as an ebook or PDF from &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/aloneinwilderne00knowgoog&quot;&gt;Archive.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/alone-in-the-wilderness</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/alone-in-the-wilderness</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ups and Downs: The 3 Best and Worst Moments of my First Cycle Tour</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I set off on my first long distance cycle tour. Inspired by the books of Al Humphreys and Mark Beaumont and their adventures travelling the world on two wheels, I saved up for a new bike with all the touring trimmings: panniers, a fancy leather saddle, and horribly uncool but ever-practical accessories such as a bell and kickstand. It had been a long time ambition of mine to go on a cycling adventure and it was exciting to finally have the means to pull at wanderlust’s thread and see familiar winding roads unravel before me and set my sights to the elusory horizon and simply go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/standing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cycled from my house in Hertfordshire, about 30 miles north of London and headed towards Edinburgh. I followed and number of Sustrans cycle routes, a network of on and off-road cycle-friendly paths, including Cycle route 1 which took me from Norfolk all the way up the east coast to Scotland. It took me 7 days to cycle 503 miles, averaging ~70 miles per day. It, for me at that time, was a long and epic journey and it came with many highs as well as lows.  Here’s my top 3 best and worst moments from my first cycle tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-3-best-moments-cycling-from-hertfordshire-to-scotland&quot;&gt;My 3 best moments cycling from Hertfordshire to Scotland&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-the-road&quot;&gt;1. On the Road&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my bike out of the shed, hopped on, said goodbye, and set off along familiar streets just as I would for any Sunday jaunt. My wheels buzzed along the hot tarmac as my mind buzzed with excitement in the knowledge that I wasn’t going to loop round on the normal circuit but instead keep going, out of the orbit of home and off on a northerly bearing towards adventure. Something I hadn’t expected but felt from the first crank was that I had already succeeded. I had planned, prepared, and embarked on an adventure that would have been easy to put off or postpone; to procrastinate from doing at each opportunity. Leaving the house that sunny morning I knew that for better or worse, through whatever challenges came in my way, it would now be easier now to face them head-on and keep going than it would be to accept defeat and turn around and come home. I had finally achieved a long-term goal of going on a long distance cycle tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/upanddown/farm.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unexpected-sights&quot;&gt;2. Unexpected Sights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By travelling by bike or on foot we choose to see the world go by at a slower pace. You get to see lots of things that you perhaps might not expect, the mundanity of journeying becomes the adventure itself bringing you to unexpected destinations that you would have otherwise missed. On my journey I heard accents change every day, subtle changes in geography and fauna, and noticed unique idiosyncrasies, such an unprecedented number of burnt mattresses in Middlesbrough or flags in Lincolnshire. Some of my favourite unexpected sights include a great string of kites in the shape of various creatures in Dunbar, and noticing these birdhouses along a rural road in Scotland. I also saved a Barn Owl that was trapped in a wire fence and met a Dutch septuagenarian who had ridden all the way from the Orkney Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/dutch.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/bike.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/lane.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/kites.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/vista.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scotland-is-cool&quot;&gt;3. Scotland is Cool&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I was most looking forward to on my trip was reaching Scotland and its relaxed camping rules that allow you to more or less wild camp anywhere. My first night beyond the border took me to a small village by the name of Foulden. Perched on the brow of a gently sloping hill, the houses of Foulden line just one side of the road, the other side saved from buildings allowing for stunning views across the Tweed Valley all the way to the distant Cheviot hills of Northumberland. I popped my tent up right there on the village green in full view of the houses. No hiding for me that night, skulking out of sight in fear of being shooed off by angry farmers. I was enjoying my right to camp freely in Scotland greatly, indeed, the next morning I was greeted by a friendly local who made me a cup of tea and filled my water bottles before I set off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/foulden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-3-worst-moments&quot;&gt;My 3 worst moments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;near-miss-with-a-nutter&quot;&gt;1. Near-miss with a Nutter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journey ended in the Scottish capital of Edinburgh, once described as a ‘mad god’s dream,’ its windy streets are lined with stone-faced tenements which can in a single moment look every bit as grand as they look austere. Built on seven hills, a qualifying foundation for many great cities, Edinburgh is centred upon a great central rock which perched upon it is a pretty sweet looking castle. I had ridden 500 miles by this time and feeling very happy to be riding through the city to my finish line, but just when I thought I had safely made it, I had a was very nearly knocked off my bike by a car cutting dangerously close in front of me. I slapped the car (classic mistake) to signal that I was there and protest his poor driving. A very angry man got out the car, shouting and swearing at me and seemingly looking for some good ol’ timey fisticuffs.  In this moment my internal fight or flight mechanism slammed down on the escape button and my legs started pedalling furiously. As I made my dash for safety I heard the car revving loudly behind me, I could see in my mirror huffs of black smoke rising from the car as it teared towards me. I bunny hopped off the road and veered off into a park and essentially hid like an idiot from a man who looked like he had murder in his eyes. That was it, I finished the ride, a little shaky but ok. In every other respect Edinburgh treated me very well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/edinburgh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;falling-off-my-bike-in-the-rain-in-hull&quot;&gt;2. Falling off my bike in the Rain in Hull&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I really need I say more? Falling off your bike is a wholly unpleasant experience at the best of times, but doing it after 40 miles of cycling in the rain, with 30 still to go only add insult to injury. It was a subtle ridge on a busy road that derailed me in the city of Hull, a place that’s most famous artwork is a picture of a dead seagull called ‘Dead Bod’ painted on a rusty shed as a joke over 50 years ago, an artwork that helped win Hull the status of Britain’s City of Culture 2017, an award that backhandedly compliments cities that aren’t London every 4 years. I scuffed my hands and knees badly and tore my shorts. I let out an involuntary but hammy yawp in front of a large audiences of drivers and pedestrians, some of which very kindly got from their cars to check I was ok. I thanked them but reassured them I was alright as I cowered off to clean my wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/bod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-perfect-storm-of-bullshit&quot;&gt;3. A Perfect Storm of Bullshit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absolute lowest moment for me came in the form of sheer exhaustion. Having ridden over 70 miles I had just another 10 to go before reaching the campsite that I had phoned earlier that day to book a spot. Last check in was 9pm, they said, any later than that and I’d be wild camping. My cycle route signalled me off the road and onto a rough looking farm track, I peeled off in good faith and kept going until I reached a hill with a gradient that only the most sinewy of cyclists could reasonably attempt. My pannier laden packhorse and my tired (and distinctly undefined) legs took one look and opted to push. Up I went, conscious of my deadline of 9pm closing in. And up and up. Glad to finally reach the top I hopped back on the bike only to ride 50 yards before blowing out a tire. It was 8:30 and I had just five miles to go but in this moment I felt so defeated I could have cried. Mustering up my last remaining scraps of mental fortitude, I got to work fixing the puncture. A quick fix and I was again on my way. Only, my road I had one more challenge in store for me. The last 2 miles of trail were finished with fist size rocks, fine for a fat bike of burly mountain bike but my spindly road tires struggled. I made it, thankfully, just in time but it really is hard to put into words how much it took out of me to get there. I pitched my tent and wandered to the pub for some much needed R+R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/rocks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/scotland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/ups-and-downs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/ups-and-downs</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scarpa Delta GTX Activ Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Quality materials and assembly&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Reduced or non-existent wearing in period&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Tough but responsive sole&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Leather isn’t for everyone&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought these Scarpas in early spring 2016, for around £180 from GoOutdoors (from a physical shop for once!) and as far as I can see, they are the tough boots from the idiom. So far I’ve covered around 500 miles in them; wading through streams, walking over hills, climbing up mountains, stomping through snow, slogging through mud, and they have yet to let so much as a drop of water in. All the while they’ve provided a high level of comfort which I didn’t have to earn with a prolonged wearing in period, they fit comfortably right out of the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Drawn in by the leather look and instantly comfortable fit, my Deltas have only improved with age.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the boot is covered in a 2.4-2.6mm leather, with a calf leather upper and tongue joint.  Although a little stiff to begin with (as leather always is) creases wore in straight away at the ankle bend, providing that tailored fit that I have only ever experienced with leather boots.  They have picked up a few cosmetic bramble scratches over the last year, while these haven’t even come close to affecting the boots performance, they have left me a little self conscious about further damage in a way I probably wouldn’t feel wearing boots with a synthetic construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stitching, glue and general construction is all fantastic quality from what I have seen in the last 12 months, nothing has budged even a little bit.  The sole has hardly aged at all, its deep tread still as effective as day one, and even the inner sole is in good condition; still springy albeit missing some surface colour from wear.  The comfort level has only increased as I have worn them in, there have been no weak links when it comes to build and material quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/quality.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A year and several hundred miles in, all of the joints and stitches show no signs of shifting.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compliment the great quality, Scarpa have realised a fantastic design to boot. They are a great mix of old and new boot style; comfortable, traditional calf and cow leather with hi-tech comfort inside and a Gore-tex waterproof lining, all topped off with a springy, bomb-proof, plastic sole. Having worn my pair in deep snow and at the height of summer without dampness creeping in and all sweat creeping out, I can say that the waterproofing and breathability of the Delta is fantastic.  The laces will stay put all day even without a lace locking mechanism and although it’s quite tricky to get the tongue to stay in place to begin with, once you have worn them enough to mould the leather into place, lacing them up is a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sole is springy and manages to feel surprisingly responsive for what is quite a large chunk of plastic, even with the very sturdy toe protector at the front. I’ve felt thoroughly connected to the earth in them almost all the time, these boots are definitely built to make you feel like Godzilla crashing down a hill, rather than a highly tuned and nimble hill walker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/design.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The memory foam, insole and springy sole work harmoniously to provide a comfort level which hasn&#39;t faded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boots have what Scarpa calls “ActivFit”, which means Scarpa made the boot using a special ‘last’ which is the analogue for a human foot used to mould the inner padding. These hi-tech lasts apparently allow for a softer padding to be used inside the boot, and this abundance of soft cushioning is what makes the boots feel better than others right out of the box. The boots also feature a breathable memory foam innersole, which really doesn’t let you down when you find yourself standing for long periods of time eating lunch or waiting for others on the trail. Without knowing about any of these features at the time, I thought they felt better than all of the other boots I tried straight away and I have only had one incident with blisters, so apparently it all works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct competitors in the 3 season leather boot range include the Mammut Brecon II, which costs ~£170 and the heavier Meindl Bhutan MFS, which costs ~£180.  Reading reviews of the competition, I am not instilled with confidence the way I was approaching Scarpa; build quality issues aren’t what you want to hear when investing in something you want to last up to 5 years.  There were actually several user reviews that included lines such as “&lt;a href=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/scarpa-review.jpg&quot;&gt;never gonna last 10 years like my old Scarpas&lt;/a&gt;”, far reaching brand reputation for quality is always a good sign.  From what I have seen, the alternative with the most to offer comes from the British company Anatom, their Braeriach 3 season boot costs only £144 and has been reviewed positively so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/worn.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a regular oil and wax I can see these boots lasting me at least another 5 years,  if they remain this comfortable I’d be happy to wear them all that time too. Insulative, grippy, comfortable and visually pleasing; they tick all the right boxes and support you in all the right places.  I’ve recently seen them online as low as £160, so while not exactly a bargain, they are still very good value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-34&quot;&gt;Rating 3/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely recommend them and would buy another pair in a heartbeat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/delta-gtx-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/delta-gtx-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going Ultralight: Repacking</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this series I’ll be taking you through my thought process as I shave the pounds off of my setup before I attempt some multiday hikes later this year.  I’ll be slimming my system down from a bloated giant which would drag me down with it, to a sleek ultralight bundle that I hardly notice as I skip along the cliffside like a mountain goat who’s just discovered weight watchers.  Hopefully you’ll find some tips that you can use with your gear, if you have any tips of your own, remember to share them in the comments!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now, the majority of my camping has involved setting up a base camp somewhere a few miles out from the car and day hiking to explore the surrounding area with only a day sack on my back.  Over the years this has led to quite a blasé attitude toward my gear purchases and how much I take with me, resulting in a very cluttered inventory of things I use rarely even though I carry them often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/start.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Just a few of the things I have recently taken out with me, mostly useful but certainly not essential.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/stuff.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The bits and bobs I&#39;ve aquired over the years always seem handy at the time but the weight adds up fast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, I have planned a few more adventurous trips which will involve hiking and camping with everything on my back for two weeks or more, this is when lighter gear starts to seem very appealing.  Being outside is great fun; hiking, cycling, canoeing, camping, these have all been enjoyed as past times since the 1800s when camping and hiking were first popularised.  Things can be made much less fun, however, if you are forced to carry enormous weight while you partake in them, as was pointed out in one of my &lt;a href=&quot;/features/how-to-camp-out&quot;&gt;favourite books&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt; &quot;Very few young men who read this book will find it possible to enjoy themselves, and carry more than twenty pounds a greater distance than ten miles a day, for a week.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was written in 1877.  Twenty pounds was more than the advised limit when hiking recreationally for an american civil war veteran.  He was surely a lot tougher than you or I, probably a fair bit stronger, and even he didn’t carry a heavy pack back when everything was made from either wool or iron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days a pack base weight of around 20lbs will class you as a ‘lightweight’ backpacker, but if it was too heavy in 1877, it’s certainly too heavy for my flimsy millennial bones today.  A pack weighing 5lbs will apparently see you classified as a ‘super-ultralight’ or ‘hyperlight’ backpacker.  From what I have seen, this weight is where you enter the realms of record breaking, astonishingly fast hikers who blaze past you with no time to concentrate on the scenery or get a trail name that doesn’t involve a superlative.  These hikernators usually forgo every creature comfort they can to save weight, and eat only food with the highest of calorie to weight ratios.  Because I’m not keen on re-hydrated beans, and wouldn’t mind the odd cup of coffee on the trail, I’m going to aim for the middle-ground. 10lbs. Ultralight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m going to be making my trips in the summer (albeit a British summer) I’m going to presume a night temperature of around 10 Celsius and infrequent rain, so I’ll create my ultralight system with that in mind.  I’ll also aim for a system with a stove of some sort because I like warm meals at night and coffee in the morning but I am open to the idea of going stoveless, depending on my final weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;repacking&quot;&gt;Repacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in lightening my pack is also the easiest and certainly the cheapest, I’m going to unpack everything and start from the beginning.  Starting from the bottom is going to force me to tackle everything I put into my pack; I’m looking at each item in a new light now, a revealing, minimalist, white light which isn’t flattering to anything but the essential.  I’m going to need to really think about how important everything is before I put it in my bag, and it’s likely my bag can lose some weight too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I repacked the first time, I picked up only the things which are directly linked to my survival outdoors; water, shelter and food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/final.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My essential gear.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how my gear looks post repack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karrimor aluminium bottle 1.5L - 143g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lifeventure collapsible bottle - 52g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water purification tablets (x 30) - 10g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 205g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shelter--sleep-system&quot;&gt;Shelter (+ Sleep System)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alpkit Hunka - 390g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vango sleeping bag - 1621g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roll mat - 150g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 2161g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cooking&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trangia Mini - 360g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meths container - 38g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spoon - 10g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 408g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;total&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gear - 2774g&lt;br /&gt;
Regatta Survivor 65 pack - 1569g&lt;br /&gt;
Total pack base weight - &lt;strong&gt;4343g&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;9lb 9.19oz&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already hit a decent starting point, and it’s only taken about 20 minutes.  Unless you’re cooking on a portable aga, at this point you should be pretty significantly below 15lbs, if not more, like me.  Here we have the essentials, as they were in my original pack, not particularly expensive or light but we’re already hovering around our goal weight.  Obviously there’s still a fair bit to add if I want to have a nice time while I hike: toiletries and perhaps some camp clothes, but we’ll get to that later in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s actually quite a lot we can do to reduce the weight even at this point, that’s what I’ll be doing in part two of this series: Refining the essential - look out for that in April!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/going-ultralight-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/going-ultralight-1</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sunix 120 Headtorch Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Rechargeable&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Useful Modes&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Compact&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Long battery life&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Comes loose easily&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;No over head strap&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought this Sunix headtorch from Amazon.co.uk in the summer of 2015 for roughly £16, I have used it almost daily since that time while jogging, camping and hiking at night.  I chose this headtorch mainly because it was the cheapest rechargeable headtorch I could find, but since purchase the durability and performance of the product has constantly surprised me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/head.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Modes for all occasions, outstanding battery life and an incredibly reasonable pricepoint make up for the flimsy feel appearance and feel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-quality&quot;&gt;Build Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard of the materials used in the construction point to an origin somewhere in China, that is to say they aren’t the highest quality; the strap feels like very cheap plastic, as does the headtorch itself.  After some Googling I found that “Sunix” doesn’t appear to have a website, and the same model can be seen branded as a “Shuofang Spower” elsewhere.  This probably means that you shouldn’t expect much to come from the lifetime warranty guaranteed on the Amazon page, but the good news is that it seems to function well enough that you shouldn’t need to find out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LEDs, buttons, water-resistant seals, charging port and peripheral bag and charging cable are all of acceptable, if somewhat lacking quality, but nothing has broken in two years of near constant use.  I have exposed the IPX 6 sealing of the unit to many a rain, sleet and snow shower while jogging and hiking, but nothing seems to have penetrated, and the LEDs are still working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/front.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The unit looks quite nice while remaining functional; the button is large enough to operate easily even with thick gloves on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical design of the unit is fairly nice, the single button gives a satisfying click and springy response, navigating the modes with different clicking patterns is very easy indeed, as well as being simple enough to memorise straight away.  For me, the one thing the design is missing is an over head strap, just to make it that bit more secure, because the lateral strap can works itself loose quite fast when you’re running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit features a bright, 120 lumen spotlight mode, with a 50 lumen floodlight setting for normal use around camp, both of these can be set to strobe with three successive button clicks.  The red night light mode is bright enough to  perform any tasks around camp without ruining your night vision, a must for any stargazers, and very handy if the inside of your tent is white or reflective.  There are also charging and over-discharging warning lights to let you know when you might be damaging the life of the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m constantly surprised by the length of burn time I can get out of the battery, if I use it an hour a day jogging in the evening, with the odd camp thrown in, I probably charge it once every 2 months, sometimes longer.  The provided 4 inch micro USB charging cable weighs roughly 10 grams so you can carry it everywhere, just in case you need a boost on the trail.  Micro USB means you can pack just one cable to charge your phone and headtorch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/charge.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A full charge takes around 30 minutes, mine tends to go a month or two between charges when I use it for an hour a night for jogging.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The torch, strap and charging cable all pack down to a handy pocket sized lump in the provided black dry bag.  Everything packed weighs only 119 grams (4.2 ounces) so it’s no hassle to throw in any coat or bag, even on longer trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;If you squash it into a coat pocket, the whole lot will compress down to a 3&quot; x 3&quot; ball.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatives to the Sunix 120 within the same price range seem to be either unbranded cheap tat, require normal AAA batteries, require you to buy separate rechargeable batteries or weigh a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petzl are generally regarded as the top dog in the world of headtorches but that comes with a bump in price, the Petzl Tikka matches the functionality of the Sunix but you’ll have to drop a further £20 on top of the ~£20 unit cost if you want a rechargeable battery pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sunix, although a bit tacky on first impressions, is astonishingly good value for what is a very handy and feature-laden item.  It’s served me well over nearly two years of jogging in all weather as well as being handy to read by in a tent.  I don’t think you can find a better headtorch for less than £25, let alone £16, it’s the outdoor gear holy grail; light, compact, cheap, reliable, convenient.  I have since bought a second one for my father to use in the garage/under cars, he is sold on it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating: 4/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this price, this is the best head torch I’ve seen.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/sunix-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/sunix-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Camp Out by John Mead Gould</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The first book to be featured as Boldly Goes’ outdoor book of the month is one of the first books written about recreational camping.  ‘How to Camp Out’ was written in 1877 by American Civil War veteran John Mead Gould, he wanted to popularise recreational hiking and camping, and especially inspire the young of the USA to go out and experience what they could while they were able.  I read the entire guide in a single sitting and made notes of interesting techniques and notable quotes as I went, finishing with quite a long list.  The book definitely succeeded in inspiring me to get outside and make the most of my youth, I immediately put some of the skills I had read of in practice and began to take Gould’s advice on note taking very seriously.  It is part of the reason I wanted to start Boldly Goes to begin with and you will no doubt see me quote its timeless wisdom in future articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
&quot;Consequently, write what you can, and let it stand with all its blots, errors, and nonsense. And be careful, when you are five years older, not to go through the diary with eraser and scissors; for, if you live still another five years, nothing will interest you more than this diary with all its defects.&quot;   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preface really tells you everything you need to know about this book; it summarises the advice of a very experienced outdoorsman with the intention of inspiring the young people of the USA to go out and experience everything nature has to offer.  Gould does this by systematically providing all of the information they would need to assemble a travelling party of their own and survive outdoors for an extended period of time.  This includes a briefing on all of the important aspects of camping, from  which equipment to buy and how to cook on an open fire  to advice on how to take useful notes on your trip, with a view to write them up for posterity later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book continues with 11 chapters detailing everything the youth of 1877 needed to know to prepare and set out into the, then very, wild American countryside.  He begins with the preparations you might need to make before you leave and recommends leaving all but the essentials behind to save pack weight.  Then he moves on through the equipment and tasks which you’ll be using and performing when camping and provides a quick but thorough summary of best practises to prepare you.  Very few people will find it useful know know about loading a pack onto a horse and cart then walking next to it up a mountain these days, but these less applicable snippets provide a window into outdoor life in the 1800s, they have a different value.  This is the beauty of Gould’s guide; it contains a lot of techniques that remain the same today, and anything outdated provides an insight into the history of camping and hiking, there are no wasted chapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words on the versatility of a wool rug inspired me to drag our old family wool blend picnic rug from the car and give it a go, I was pleasantly surprised to find it was extremely useful in the woods where the Boldly Goes team usually camps.  Rolled up and slung over the shoulder, it’s a comfortable, if a bit warm, way to carry clothes and food.  Folded it provides a nice seat or sleeping mat in the summer, and it stops the wind wicking away the warmth from your sleeping bag when wrapped around it.  It’s obviously a bit heavy, but if you’re camping overnight and aren’t walking too far, it’s definitely a nice thing to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/marchbotm/rug.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;As well as keep you warm in the evenings, a wool rug makes carrying extra food and water a breeze.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final two chapters of the book, Gould has included extracts in full from the work of two other experts of the day.  The first, Reverend Edward Everett Hale, has some insights into the habits you should develop while hiking as well as a cautionary tale on not taking chances of adventure when they present themselves.  The second, Dr. Elliott Coues, offers advice on avoiding injury and illness outdoors, the preventative measures like keeping warm and always maintaining three points of contact when climbing still ring true.  I would, however, advise finding some more up-to-date information on reviving a drowned man that doesn’t involve rubbing their face to make it warm, them splashing cold water on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt; &quot;Be independent, but not impudent. See all you can, and make the most of your time; &quot;time is money;&quot; and, when you grow older, you may find it even more difficult to command time than money.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to Camp Out is 70 pages of distilled knowledge written in an accessible way by a man whose clear love for the outdoors and passion for teaching others shines throughout the book, making it a pleasure to read.  It’s a lovely little piece of nourishing history which I’d definitely recommend to keen outdoorsmen who are beginners or seasoned experts.  Both will come away from the book having learned different things: the newer, perhaps some new techniques and tips; the more experienced, some perspective on their outdoor skills and gear, and how little the basics have changed in 140 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to Camp Out is available for free as an ebook or PDF via the &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.org/stream/howtocampout17575gut/17575.txt&quot;&gt;Gutenberg project&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gutenberg.org/files/17575/17575-h/17575-h.htm&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/how-to-camp-out</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/how-to-camp-out</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hot tent camping on a shoestring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hot tent camping is where a stove is used inside of the tent to provide warmth in extremely cold conditions. “Crikey!” I hear you cry, “That sounds mighty dangerous!”. That’s because you’re right. We’ve obviously got two very clear hazards here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Risk of perishing in a raging inferno, and;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slowly succumbing to the odourless persuasions of carbon monoxide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing point number one, any hot tent camping setup needs to be carefully designed to reduce the risk of fire hazard by ensuring there is no contact with flammable materials and that the stove is stable, and will not topple. The fire also needs to be carefully monitored at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On point number two, the stove needs to have a good draw, ensuring that when it is in operation, noxious fumes are safely extracted out of the tent. Still, a downdraught is always a risk, therefore the only safe option here is that the fire must be completely extinguished when you go to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If any readers are seriously considering hot tent camping we recommend doing your research and taking all the necessary precautions when dealing with fire in a confined space. What we are demonstrating in this article is a proof-of-concept of what can be achieved with not that much money.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the construction of a mini wood burning stove made out of a beer keg. To use this in a hot tent camping setup we needed to make a couple of alterations. Namely the addition of longer chimney to extend through a hole in the tent. However, when we were testing our creation we found that the chimney became red hot. If this part came into contact with tent fabric, it would obviously be bad news. So we devised a two layer chimney; we stacked a number of old baked bean cans on top of each other then put a piece of aluminum tubing over the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/1-full.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Full of beans&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the tent Sam picked up a vintage 1974 Polish Military issue lavvu for less than £30. If you’re not aware, the lavvu is a fantastic thing indeed. A lavvu consists of two large canvas ponchos and several pieces of aluminium tubing which can be combined to make a teepee. The ponchos have one hole on either side for each arm. When fully constructed, this leaves a convenient chimney sized hole in the lavvu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/2-chimney.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Erected lavvu with protruding chimney&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we used the aforementioned two layer chimney construction we still wanted to make sure the chimney did not come into contact with the lavvu canvas. To ensure this, we wedged the opening into a rigid diamond shape using a stiff twig either side of the chimney. Let’s just take a short break to admire the glorious dying light in our chosen camping location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/3-shep.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Shepherd&#39;s delight&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, back to burning stuff. We collected some firewood, loaded the mini keg stove and built another fire nearby also. As day became night, we lit the stove and closely monitored our creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/4-cosy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Cosy living quarters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fire had got going all three of us piled into the lavvu, closed the door and basked in the intense heat quickly building in the small space. We found that the rough seal of the canvas lavvu massively helps to keep the heat from escaping and that within a matter of seconds of closing the door, the space became quite toasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/5-complete.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The completed lavvu / mini tent hot camping set up&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we didn’t sleep in the lavvu on the first night, I think we have proven that you can quite cheaply assemble a small, functional hot tent camping setup that could serve the purpose of quickly warming you up for a very small fuel load.  We’ll definitely be experimenting with this set up in the future. Breaking down the cost…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beer keg ~ £15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheet aluminum ~£2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aluminium chimney ~£10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lavvu with aluminium poles ~£30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: ~£57&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with a wonderful long exposure shot that James took of a passing plane in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;large&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/6-sky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Night trails&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/hot-tenting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/hot-tenting</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beer, fire and power tools</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The team will soon be experimenting with a different kind of camping, Hot Tent Camping. Don’t worry, we aren’t planning on restarting the Carry On… franchise. Hot tent camping involves the use of a stove to provide warmth to the tent in particularly cold conditions. It is most often used for semi permanent setups in permanently cold conditions such as way up in North Canada. In these types of setups, specialist equipment is absolutely essential, eh. Amongst such equipment is typically a large and predictably heavy log burning stove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not a group to go spending money on expensive equipment where it isn’t warranted, especially if it’s for some crackpot idea that might only be a one time use. So, we went about making our own prototype, of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product spec was simple: up-cycle materials to make a small, lightweight, portable log burning stove with a chimney which can be attached to a hole in the camping canopy. We got thinking, what would be a good size item for the main chamber? We needed to find something which could take the heat of a 250°C fire, was fairly light and just the right size; not too big, not too small. Our solution was found in another one of the team’s shared hobbies, drinking beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many supermarkets and microbreweries sell mini kegs which hold around 5 litres of beer. We wagered that one of these would be ideal as the starting point and first building block for our lightweight stove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/1-plan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A plan is made&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a plethora of spare materials and some roughly sketched plans we would have promptly begun construction, except for one small problem. Our mini beer keg was still full of beer. Fortunately, with the help of my dad (whom was kindly providing use of workshop and many provisions), that issue was swiftly resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/2-sam.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sam (not my dad)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we needed to make a hole in the top of the keg to make room for a chimney. Looking at the wide selection of tools available to us we chose our weapon and quickly found that the stainless steel keg cut like butter at the hands of most sharp edges, especially a quickly oscillating jigsaw blade. After drilling several pilot holes we cut an opening in the top and folded in the lips. Following our theme of a low budget scrapheap challenge, we then inserted our next part, an old baked bean can for the chimney. After some gentle coercion this fit as snug as a bug in a rug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/3-can.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This can can&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we needed to cut a hole and make some kind of door mechanism which would be simple to make but also easy to place and remove when the stove is burning away. The team sketched up a few different ideas and eventually settled upon the idea of placing a door, consisting of an appropriately shaped piece of sheet aluminium, on a small lip at the top of an opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/4-hole.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Holely satisfying&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then gutted the belly of the beast, drilling out the dispenser nozzle and several ventilation holes around the bottom, which would hopefully provide some draw of air. We also cut out the aluminum door and attached some wire to act as hook. Finally we cut out and bent some strips of aluminium to act as stage to hold the firewood above the bottom of the keg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/5-finished.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished Article&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I swear that whenever the Boldly Goes team gets together, we end up making a fire; this occasion was no exception. We loaded the mini-keg stove with paper and kindling, lit the fire and put on the door. Within a minute the fire was roaring and an impressive draw was pulling the flame out the top of the old baked bean can chimney. We kept adding more kindling to the fire and quickly found that we had made a very hungry little stove indeed; it will tear through its maximum capacity of kindling in about five minutes flat. After which, the stove is quickly cool to the touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/6-safe.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This will be totally safe in a tent, right?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We burnt the stove for about 20 minutes in an attempt to burn off any of the paint or surface finishes on the keg which may produce noxious fumes. Investigating the state of the stove after it had cooled down we’d found that it had adopted a rustic blackened tinge inside and out. We also found that our aluminum fire stage inside had not survived the intense heat of the fire and had curled away to a thin wisp. Considering our creation and testing fairly successful, we’re now ready to incorporate this into a &lt;a href=&quot;/features/hot-tenting&quot;&gt;hot tent setup. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
