<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BOLDLY GOES</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 14:21:16 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 14:21:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Lake District: Wild Camping and Black Sail</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Black Sail is a pretty special youth hostel. It has a reputation as one of the most inaccessible youth hostels in the UK. Based in the heart of the Lake District, it is only accessible by either a six mile trek up the valley from Ennerdale (not the TV show) or by mountain pass. However, just because it’s remote, that doesn’t mean it isn’t popular. The hostel is closed over the colder months (November thru to March) and has just 16 beds (eight male and eight female), which means that the weekends over the popular summer season get booked up fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We managed to bag four beds on a Sunday night in May by booking the previous October and then decided to plan a slightly bigger trip around that booking. The Lake District does not legally permit wild camping but it is tolerated as long as some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lakedistrict.gov.uk/visiting/where-to-stay/wild-camping&quot;&gt;quite reasonable rules&lt;/a&gt; are followed. After driving up from Hertfordshire on the Friday we stopped off at The Twa Dogs in Keswick to plan a route and general wild camping spots for the Friday and Saturday nights, taking us to Black Sail on Sunday night and back to the car on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/1-planning.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Totally non-staged route planning photo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time was not on our side on Friday night (&lt;em&gt;just one beer never means just one beer&lt;/em&gt;), we picked out potential camping spots on the OS map. We rocked up to a candidate spot in the black of night, considered it suitable, pitched up and hit the hay. Late night wild campers can’t be choosers. When the sun rose, and the rain settled in, we were greeted with a proper view of our site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/2-morning.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Good morning wood&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After packing up, we made a swift visit to Keswick to pick up supplies, grab some brekkie and then we were ready to start our trip proper. Black Sail is conveniently placed within (reasonable) walking distance to England’s tallest mountain, Scafell Pike. With that in mind, our route on Saturday took us into the belly of the Lake District, allowing us to tackle Scafell Pike and finish the walk to Black Sail throughout Sunday. We parked the car in Stonethwaite, the start of our circular route, and set off through Langsrath Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/3-blea.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Blea[k] Rock&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture a round of the popular British TV quiz show, QI (I’m picturing it before Sandi Toksvig, when Stephen Fry was still presenting). A stock photo of the Lake District pops up behind our guests (let’s go for Daniel Radcliffe sitting next to Alan Davies, with David Mitchell and Ulrika Jonsson on the opposite side). Stephen forms a question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now, moving on to our glorious national parks. It is well known that the Lake District is ironically home to taller peaks than any located in the Peak District. The Lake District, of course, contains England’s tallest mountain, Scafell Pike. The choice of name for the Peak District is better understood by the number of peaks located in the Peak District, 108 of which are over the height of 245m. However, do you know how many lakes there are in the Lake District?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan chirps up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I went on a family holiday to the Lake District when I was 11. My resounding memories from the trip were rain and me and my sister arguing about who would be the dog in Monopoly for the fifth game in a row.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Light audience snicker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David interjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve got a very old version of Monopoly in our household. So old in fact that all the original playing pieces have all long gone missing. So when you’re picking your piece, that means you have a choice of: a green army man, a large black button, a tiny comb, a fridge magnet of the letter “C”, a thimble (but not the one from the original version) and a laminated picture of Alan Titchmarsh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience guffaws&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan, ever the fool, goes for the contrary answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I bet there’s some stupid meaning for what a “lake” is; I’m going for zero”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SIRENS WAIL&lt;/em&gt; The screen flashes “0”, “0”, “0”. Alan rolls his eyes and Stephen smiles from ear to ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Not quite Alan, anyone else?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel gives it a shot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I haven’t been to the Lake District but my family does have a version of Monopoly with my face on the board. That’s just one item from the many in my Mum’s weirdly obsessive Harry Potter memorabilia collection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conscientious audience laughter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Complete stab in the dark for this one, I’m going for 52”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen smiles once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Looks like your natural wizarding talent didn’t help you out. Any more for any more?”. Ulrika stares blankly and Stephen continues. “Well, Alan nearly had this one”, the screen behind changes to a picture of Bassenthwaite Lake, “There is only one lake in our district of lakes. Whilst there are many bodies of water within the Lake District, it is only Bassenthwaite Lake, close to Keswick which has “lake” in its title. However, there are 16 other bodies of water which are considered to be the main “lakes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All guests roll their eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/4-angle.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clouds part for a short rest at Angle Tarn (not a lake)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a morning of rain, the clouds part as we made our way up to Bow Fell. Still, it was a short reprise; as we reached the last stretch to the peak we were greeted by a mighty wind which cut through to your core. I think the name of its sister mountain, Crinkle Crags, pretty aptly describes the type of rocks right at the top of Bow Fell. The well trodden path towards the peak of Bow Fell disappears 20 metres before the summit and becomes a crinkly craggy scramble (or difficult to traverse interbeds of andesite outcropping from the ground).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/5-bowfell.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from atop Bow Fell&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Bow Fell we descended into the South-Western valley, the area which we’d decided to hunt for a suitable camping spot. At the base of the valley runs Lingcove Beck, a beautiful river which hides new pools and waterfalls around every twist and turn. We located a fine flat piece of grass right next to the picturesque glen at Throstle Garth. A mere two minutes after  we’d dropped our bags on the ground we stripped down to our pants, scrambled down the rocks and had a (very) brief dip in our private pool. If you’re into canyoning, wild swimming or just getting cold and wet; I would heartily recommend this stretch of water to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/6-camping.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Overlooking our camping spot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this trip I brought with me a long held but never used camping accessory, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00FA2RLX2/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00FA2RLX2&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=bolgoe-21&amp;amp;linkId=2482677efd77bd804fcd499be81d1241&quot;&gt;Sawyer Mini water filtration system&lt;/a&gt;. After using it to continually replenish all four of our water supplies throughout the trip, I cannot understate what a fantastic piece of kit this is. This 60g filter uses a fibre membrane to filter out 99.99999% of bacteria. Without getting too technical, the force of the flow sends water through hundreds of U shaped micro tubes; these micro tubes have tiny 0.1 micron pores which capture and stop any bacteria, allowing only clean water to pass. We sat by the stream in the morning and filled up 10 litres of water in about 10 minutes. It most certainly beats relying on water purification tablets; the water comes out crystal clear and has a crisp, clean taste to it (which, in hindsight, is probably more a property of the water from the Lake District springs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/7-water.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Replenishing water supplies with the Sawyer filtration system&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday morning we began our ascent towards Scafell Pike. After getting stuck knee deep in mud during my &lt;a href=&quot;/features/wild-camping-dartmoor&quot;&gt;previous solo trip to Dartmoor&lt;/a&gt;, I was wary of the telltale signs of a bog when crossing Great Moss to the base of Scafell Pike. With patient caution we navigated our way through and surveyed our route up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/8-ascent.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Contemplating the ascent of Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring Scafell Pike is another peak, Scafell. Which, from many angles, including the southerly route we approached from, appears taller than Scafell Pike. Whilst Scafell Pike is regularly traversed by coach-led tourists, Scafell is a popular draw for climbers. UKC (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukclimbing.com/articles/page.php?id=2853&quot;&gt;UKClimbing.com&lt;/a&gt; calls Scafell “England’s finest cliff” with a “sublime climbing experience that is second to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/9-spooky.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;2spooky4me&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we reached the top of Scafell Pike we stopped for lunch, making sure to take all our rubbish with us. Why do I mention this? Well, much like our favourite celebrities, there is often a cruel price that must be paid for fame. Wasdale Mountain Rescue Team has a long history of posting scathing statuses on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/WasdaleMRT/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; relating to the state of England’s tallest peak: “Shocking amounts of litter, people creating new paths, the stink of urine and worse on the summit of Scafell Pike this morning”. They also posed the question of whether a climb to the peak was the highlight of the day, or a trip to the tip. I can’t really attest to seeing a huge amount of rubbish, well, except for a Liverpool FC flag which someone had attached to the summit marker…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/10-celebration.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Slight premature celebration on Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading back down the north side of the hill we were met with breathtaking views of Great Gable (claim to fame at 9th tallest mountain in England) and the surrounding scenery. This valley leads all the way to Wasdale Head, the most common place to embark on the climb to Scafell Pike; therefore, there is a pub. The Wasdale Head Inn has great home-fry style chips but to its discredit, it does not serve &lt;em&gt;Scafell Pint&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/11-greatgable.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View down to Great Gable just off Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Wasdale Head we embarked on the final stretch of the day, Black Sail Pass. Tired, and legs heavy we were delighted to see Black Sail Youth Hostel nestled in the side of the hill as we descended into the valley of River Liza. We were met by the welcoming James who checked us in, cooked us dinner and sold us wine. Key tip if you’re staying at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yha.org.uk/hostel/black-sail&quot;&gt;Black Sail&lt;/a&gt;, bring cash! The central area in Black Sail has tables and benches which surround a roaring wood-burning stove. Placards on the walls also answer the age old riddle: what came first? Black Sail or Black Sail Pass? You’ll have to go yourself to find out the answer out to that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/12-blacksail.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Last stretch to Black Sail&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning we were cooked breakfast and given packed lunches (I promise this wasn’t a school trip). We donned full waterproof gear, having been extremely lucky with the weather up to that point, and headed towards Honister Pass. The final stretch back to the car took us along the road through Seatoller where we paused, you know, just because we like standing around in the rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/13-wet.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;W e t b o y e s&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completing our circular route at Stonethwaite we found a conveniently placed bus stop to change out of our wet things; all of us experiencing the familiar feeling of satisfied tiredness that comes from getting lost in nature for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/14-dry.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dry&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/black-sail</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/black-sail</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 Hours: in the Wicklow Mountains</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick dash to Dublin on the plane and an hour’s drive south will bring you to the Wicklow mountains. I set off on a friday night after work, sunk a few pints of Guinness, hiked all day Saturday, and was back in time for Sunday dinner. Here’s a few of the pictures I took during my time in these fine hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/1-lugnaquilla.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ascending Lugnaquilla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wicklow mountains make up the largest expanse of moors and uplands in Ireland, its highest point is Lugnaquilla standing at 925m, which although tall still falls short of those in County Kerry. It takes just over an hour to drive out from Dublin to the base of Lugnaquilla, if you take the scenic route, which will reward you with views of vast bleak moors for sure, on a good day views of the Irish Sea, and if you keep your eyes peeled, the odd christmas tree dressed up with tinsel and baubles - no I’m not joking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/2-cloghernagh.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nice looking cairn at the summit of Cloghernagh&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just a few hours of walking we were treated with sun, bitter wind, sleet, hail, and rain. Fortunately we were prepared and didn’t suffer too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/3-summit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The top of Lugnaquilla, the tallest mountain in the Wicklow’s, standing at 925m&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit of Lugnaquilla, which translates to ‘hollow of the wood’, consists of a wide plateau. The ascent is mostly very gentle and we were surprised at how quickly we summited the mountain. There are steep faces on either side named ‘north prison’ and ‘south prison’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/4-nicespot.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;I’d quite like to move here&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a circular route which began in Glenmalur where there is a car park just south of the Glenmlure Hostel. The ascent begins on a wide forestry road but quickly turns into an easy scramble up 100 metre or so, which really was the only the challenging section of the walk, but certainly nothing to worry about. From then it’s just a matter of keeping on the path and not getting caught out but sphagnum bogs - &lt;a href=&quot;/features/wild-camping-dartmoor&quot;&gt;something Harvey learned a lot about in Dartmoor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/5-ireland.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Just one of the many beautiful spots Ireland treated us to&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the summit of Lugnaquilla we descended via Cloghernagh, the location of the cairn pictured earlier. From there it’s an easy descent back down to the road and walk back to the car park. The whole hike took us about 5 hours, which was taking at a gentle pace and the total length is roughly 10 miles, making this an easy hike that more or less anyone could enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/6-weather.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching inclement weather&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some more pics from my trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-6.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-wicklow</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-wicklow</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OS Maps App Review</title>
        <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;price&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free from App store and Google Play &lt;br /&gt;
1 month subscription: £3.99&lt;br /&gt;
1 year subscription: £23.99&lt;br /&gt;
Or use redeem code from a paper map to download an area&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurate route planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offline downloads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPS location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drains battery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the incredible progress of the digital world in the past decade many outdoor enthusiasts and adventurers still find themselves reaching for a paper map before setting out for an adventure. We’re lucky in the UK to have fantastic maps in the form of Ordnance Survey 1:25k and 1:50k. They are a joy to use due to their accuracy and excellent design. Of course there have been great strides in mapping technology such as those made by GPS, however, devices are still expensive and not an option for everyone. That’s where the OS maps app steps in, offering digital versions of our favourite maps from our phones, a device most people already possess, offering a cheap way to access the accuracy and solace afforded by a GPS device. We were excited at the prospect but how well does it work? A part of me thought that it must be too good to be true. We’ve been using the app for the last few months and here’s what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has several types of map available to use for different purposes including the standard 1:25k and 1:50 OS maps as well as as  typical road map for use in the car, plus another for when driving at night. It also offer satellite imagery as well as an ‘offroad routing’ map which is a simplified style, not dissimilar from the Google/Apple/Bing map style, but with contours and paths shown in National Park areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be noted that you will not be able to access 25k and 50k maps without either using a redeem code found in all new OS landranger and explorer maps to download an area, or by paying a subscription, giving access to nationwide mapping, either monthly or annually. You can then save these maps for offline use as and when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also plot routes for either running, walking, or cycling, which you can save and share if you like. The app will show how long your route is, elevation data, and provide an estimated time needed to complete the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-use&quot;&gt;In Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time I’ve been using the app I have found it to be very reliable and useful. The practicalities of being able to quickly glance at a phone beats stopping to unfold a map, particularly in windy conditions. I have found the GPS location to be very accurate even when far away from mobile service. Obviously you need to be wary about the safety of your device, most mobile devices are still vulnerable to damage whilst being used in adverse conditions. I use a Quadlock phone case with a rain cover which I would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/1-title.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/2-options.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/3-derwent1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/4-derwent2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/5-route.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/6-sharing.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highly recommend this app. It functions very well and is reliable when you need it to be, although I would still recommend using it in addition to a physical map and compass, rather than solely relying on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating: 4/4&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/os-app-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/os-app-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Q&amp;A with Mark Beaumont</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We spoke with Mark Beaumont, one of Britain’s top adventurers, as he puts together his final preparations before setting off around the world on two wheels in an attempt to break the world record (for a second time no-less). Mark has been adventuring since an early age, cycling the Land’s End to John O’Groats aged just fifteen. Since then he has cycled the world in record time, rowed across oceans, and travelled the length of Africa on two wheels in just 42 days. I first came across Mark when I read his book ‘The Man who Cycled the World’, I owe this book a great deal for showing what’s possible on two wheels when you put your mind to it, and for giving me and doubtless, countless others the inspiration to hit the road in search of adventure. For this reason I was very pleased to get just a little of his time to ask a few questions before he sets off on his next big adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beaumont/bike.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. What do we need to know about you 80 days adventure? How we can we support and follow your journey?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. Having cycled around the World unsupported ‘wild man’ style in 194 days a decade ago, I have always wondered how much quicker I could go if I had full support and trained professionally.  Around the World in 80 Days has taken the last few years in the planning and will mean riding 16 hours a day for 75 days, with 3 days of flight and 2 days contingency.  The current circumnavigation World Record is 123 days held by Andrew Nicholson from New Zealand, and so I aim to take this down by around 43 days.  Success for me would be coming home safely, including my whole support team, and feeling that we have left absolutely everything out there.  The golden standard is around the World in 80 Days, as this would be a one-time prize - you won’t remember the second person to go sub 80!  You can follow at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.artemisworldcycle.com&quot;&gt;artemisworldcycle.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://markbeaumontonline.com/&quot;&gt;markbeaumontonline.com&lt;/a&gt; and through social media at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MarkBeaumontAdventures/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mrmarkbeaumont?lang=en&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/mrmarkbeaumont/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. For the bike nerds, can you tell us a little about your setup and gear, does it differ much from your previous round the world cycle?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. The bike is a KOGA Kimera Pro which is carbon frame, with Ultregra Di2 and hydraulic disc brakes.  I am riding 47mm carbon Corima rims with Panaracer 28mm Dura tires,  Drops and tai-bars are Profile Design.  The aero helmet is a Rudy Project and the clothing is Altura custom made kit.  This is a very different set-up to a decade ago, but quite similar to what I rode down Africa a few years ago, where I broke the Cairo to Cape Town record by a margin of 18 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beaumont/rain.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. You are considered one of the best endurance adventurers in the world right now, how did this come about? What or who do you attribute your ability and success to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. That is kind - I have never entered a race, so never really consider my performance in relation to any other athletes.  What I have always done, since I was a twelve year old boy pedalling across Scotland, is take on journeys that inspire me, and try to share them in as big and as interesting a way as I can.  Taking a global audience along on the journey is important to me, and adds fuel to the fire, and I know it inspires a lot of people as well, so is hugely valuable.  I have worked with some amazing people, including the late, great David Peat, who taught me the art and love of documentary film-making.  And at the heart of my work is my family - basecamp is run by my mum Una, and my wife and two daughters are amazingly supportive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. In your lowest moments on the road what strategies do you use to cope and keep on riding?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. The toughest times become your fondest memories.  The only thing worse than going slowly is stopping.  Momentum is your only friend in tough times.  Giving up isn’t an option unless it’s a case of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q. You’ve seen more of the world than most ever will and seen many cultures. In your experience how are people the same and how are they different?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. The more you see, the more you realise there is to see - I have travelled to about 130 nations and territories in my life and I now have a very positive impression humanity, despite having been in  many tight corners, but I am also increasingly aware of our incredible diversity and differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beaumont/team.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Artemis World Cycle Team. (All photos coutesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.artemisworldcycle.com&quot;&gt;artemisworldcycle.com&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/mark-beaumont-interview</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/mark-beaumont-interview</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kielder Observatory and Skyspace</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/kielder/sunset.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries Northumberland was a land of wild lawlessness, be it from the times of the Roman Empire when Hadrian’s wall marked the edge of civilisation, keeping the rebellious Picts at bay, or from the days of the Scottish Marches, when Reivers raided the lands, running protections rackets called ‘mál’s’, leading us to the modern word Blackmail. Indeed, Northumberland, the northernmost part of England, has throughout history been a bleak and dangerous place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/rocks.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I stood next to the Hadrian’s wall, high up on the edge of Walltown Crags, on a cloudless day, it was hard to imagine Northumberland’s turbulent past. Indeed, today it is a place for tourists to leisurely admire. And come to think of it, it’s also place of many superlatives: it is, afterall, home to the largest forest, the darkest skies, and the sparsest population in England and Wales. Yet it is the least visited of our national parks. For all of its rugged history and vast swaths of hills, forests, and moorland, the National park seems to have passed most of us by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/portrait.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that piqued my interest in visiting the park was its status as an International Dark Space: it offers the best views of the night skies in England and has the largest area of protected night skies in Europe. I am certainly no more than a casual astronomer at best and have never really seen an unpolluted night sky. So I jumped at the chance to visit. Here are some more pictures from my trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/observatory.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The winning design: created by Charles Barclay architects of London, chosen from from 230 design entries&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/telescopes.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The small telescopes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/hall.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; The Skyspace is an echoic subterranean hall with an apertured ceiling for viewing the sky with the naked eye&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/car.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/kielder-observatory</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/kielder-observatory</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alpkit Compact Ultra Twins Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great Value for Money&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small pack size&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Quick release locking mechanism&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Nordic style handle not to everyone’s taste&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small and fiddly hand strap&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Not always practical for tarp camping&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compact ultra is a collapsible pole that folds down to a very short 38cm, making it very packable and particularly convenient for plane travel, trail running or climbing. The pole is assembled by slotting the sections together, much like a tent pole, and then pulling one end to put tension into an internal cable that is then locked in place by snap lock. You can then adjust the top half of the pole to your desired length and secure with the single quick release locking mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/collapsed.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handle is a Nordic style design with a non detachable velcro hand strap. It is worth noting for those who may not have encountered this style of grip that you cannot use the pole with your hand on top of the handle, like a walking stick, as the size and shape of the grip makes this uncomfortable. Likewise, it’s worth pointing out that while the hand strap is well made and looks really nice donning its Alpkit logo, it is rather small and fiddly making it hard to put on quickly. I found this design fine for long flattish walks where I could consistently hold the poles for long stretches of time but rather annoying on more technical hikes where I wanted to take my hand out of the straps often and quickly. If you plan to wear gloves in conjunction with these poles you may find it difficult to fit your hand in the strap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to point out with this design is that while its collapsed length is very short, its minimum erected length is rather long (insert cock gag here) making it not particularly versatile for tarp camping where you may need shorter pole for your setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the relatively tiny £34 price tag of these poles there’s question that quality you can expect would be lower than more expensive and familiar alternative options from the likes of Leki or Black Diamond. What you can expect here is a very compact folding pole that mostly bears the hallmarks of a product at its price but with a couple of nice features added in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hand strap, albeit small, is nicely made and I found it quite comfortable. I would prefer if it had a quick release clip or was simply larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/strap.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal cable that runs down the centre of the pole is protected by a fairly thin plastic sheath. I noticed that when the pole is collapsed this cable is pulled tight against the edges of the pole segments, right now mine are holding strong but I will keep an eye on them as it looks vulnerable to damage, and if the cable breaks the pole become useless, something you wouldn’t want to happen on any long hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this price, finding a branded alternative is quite difficult particularly one of this style with similar features. For instance any Leki pole that collapses as small as this will certainly cost more than £100, and the cheapest trekking pole they sell is still £5 more than the Alpkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/fullpole.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need a pole that packs particularly small and you are on a budget, this is an excellent option. You can for the price, expect to forgo some practicalities and some quality, but ultimately Alpkit has succeeded here in filling a space in the market for an imaginatively designed product delivered at an unbeatable price. I would have rated this product 3/4 if the handle and strap where just a little better and easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-24&quot;&gt;Rating 2/4&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/compact-ultra-twins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/compact-ultra-twins</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Borough Bivvy Bagging</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s 4.30 in the morning. I’m in a beautiful nature reserve in the London borough of Barking and Dagenham, in what should be very peaceful surroundings for sleeping out beneath the night sky. However, reality at this time was not quite that serene and rather than being snug in my bivvy bag and sound asleep, I found myself up a tree instead. Oh the joy and adventure of the great outdoors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/hammersmith.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Hammersmith and Fulham&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it all began…I’ve been a fan of sleeping outdoors for quite some time now. Laying there beneath a canvas of stars, with nothing but a couple of layers of material and my face exposed to that deep dark blue night sky, with a cool sweet breeze upon my face. My idea of bliss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to do all my wild camping in tents; it was great fun and cheaper than staying in hostels and b&amp;amp;bs but then I discovered the bivouac. This was at the break of Spring in 2014, and I haven’t looked back since that first undertaking. I developed such a bug for it that I have now slept outdoors without a tent 132 times (not that I’m counting or anything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My passion is for long distance walking which consists of a linear route that lasts 5 to 10 days. During these trips a bivvy at the end of the day can be very rewarding and usually guarantees a good night’s sleep. It’s always good to escape the city for a while, leaving all that mayhem behind and allowing yourself to reset. Obviously living and working in London means I can’t always get away when I want, so a couple of years ago I thought why not bring the adventure to my doorstep and try bivvying in London itself. At that time I thought this was surely a terrible idea and probably not possible but one late august evening I decided to give it a go; venturing out with a friend to Hackney Downs to attempt our first bivvies in London. I went into this thinking of all the things that could go wrong; the sheer population of London, the state of some of its’ green spaces, and a general fear of the unknown. Upon waking up in the morning I was pleasantly surprised to find I had had an undisturbed sleep and possibly one of my best bivvys to date which ended with watching a beautiful sunrise over a sleepy East London skyline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/hackney.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The first one, London Borough of Hackney&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience gave birth to really experimenting with what is on my doorstep and led to a 30 night challenge of sleeping outdoors in London for the whole of September. Each evening I bivvied at a different location and also woke up in some of London’s famous green spots in the likes of Hyde Park, St James Park and Hampstead Heath. It was a truly eye opening challenge and gave me an immense appreciation of just how green London is and the richness it has to offer in terms of open space. Places right here at home, where you can still achieve a calm and peace, completely clearing your head and recharging your soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/westminster.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;St. James&#39; Park, London Borough of Westminster&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing this eventful experiment I was hungry for more and decided that I would walk the London Loop; a 150 mile circular route around Greater London, very much like the M25, but which acts as a green corridor around the city instead. I wanted to do this during my working week so decided to undertake it as a number of night rambles ending with a bivvy in whichever area I found myself in. It took 12 nights in total during the winter season and even saw me go on a date with my now girlfriend (we were third date in). It took me to areas of London that were completely unknown to me; such as Barnet, Hounslow, and Bexley which was another wonderful insight into how much there really is to play with and escape to within the Capital. As well as this, I realised that  the landscape of these green spaces in the city are so varied as I have been able to hammock as well as bivvy in woodland, marshes, fields and even a cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/sutton.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Sutton&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’ve always liked collecting things; whether it be postcards, football stickers, or national park bucket lists, I think they’re important fragments of what makes up our individual identity. Having worked out I’d slept outdoors in 23 of the 32 London Boroughs, I realised my latest collection would have to be bivouacking in all of the boroughs and so was born my idea of  ‘borough bivvy bagging’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/greenwich.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Greenwich&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so back to why I found myself up a tree on a Thursday night in the middle of Dagenham. I had had a solid sleep until I was awoken at 4.30 in the morning to the vibration of thuds not too far in the distance. Trying to get back off to sleep was put on hold, as they got closer, and seemed to have multiplied. Low and behold, it was only a band of wild horses that had landed at my little camp area. For the next 15 minutes it was a game of figuring out each others intentions and evidently freaking each other out, which resulted with me seeking higher ground and climbing up the nearest tree. My actions were odd enough to send them packing to the other side of the stream from which they had come and for me to slowly make my way back down to my bivvy bag with a little less pride than the beginning of the night. I lay back laughing remembering how each bivvy in London has been unique whilst witnessing another beautiful city sunrise. That was another borough bagged and ticked off the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/barking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Barking and Dagenham (with the infamous tree)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be moving out of London in 6 weeks time and relocating to the Peak District. I’m cutting it slightly fine but I fully intend on completing the challenge before I leave.  What Brent, Ealing, Croydon and the other remaining 3 will offer I don’t know. But I do believe that every little corner of London has some form of space to get lost and rediscover yourself in by escaping and enjoying the simplicity of sleeping under the stars. It hasn’t let me down so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/challenge-map.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Progress so far on my London Borough challenge map&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 down, 6 to go! And surely I need to complete the challenge with a final bivvy in the City of London (technically not a Borough) as a kind of icing on the cake. That or finally get moved on by the authorities or picked up by the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/haringey.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;With friends, London Borough of Haringey&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer of making the most of what’s on offer right in front of you, and achieving a sense of thrill and excitement by working with what you have and turning restrictions into opportunities. It’ll be an odd mantel but one that will live with me forever. So thanks for having me London.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/borough-bivvy-bagging</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/borough-bivvy-bagging</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aplkit Hunka Bivvy Bag Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great waterproofing&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Well made&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Light&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Recent price hike&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Not very windproof&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Hunka from Alpkit.com for £35 in May 2016 after seeing it recommended on Alastair Humphreys’ website.  360g seemed very appealing for overnighters when compared to my tent at the time which weighed 1.4kg, but it has proven reliable enough to be a fixture of my overnght kit even now I own a 680g tent.  If you want to get close to nature, the thin but reliable Hunka is as close as you can get while staying dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/length.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;At 215cm x 80cm the Hunka just about accommodates my normal length sleeping bag. Anyone over 6&#39;1&quot; will want to upgrade to the Hunka XL.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alpkit listed the Hunka’s country of origin as China on their website so when I saw the price, even when I took the reviews into account, I expected lacking build quality and materials.  As soon as I opened the package I could feel the ripstop nylon was smooth and almost luxurious, all my fears faded and have stayed in hiding as the product has made it through it’s first year not just intact, but like new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hems and joints show no sign of weakness on the Hunka, they are mostly stitched twice and have been finished well, I found no loose threads anywhere on mine.  Inside, the seams are taped very securely and almost invisibly; I have packed, scrunched and folded my Hunka hundreds of times and they show no sign of budging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/stitching.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;All of the seams are rock solid, the tape on the inside isn&#39;t going anywhere either.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawcord and clasp at the opening and on the footbox net feel slightly plasticy and stuck a little to begin with, but now I have worn them in they function smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been rudley woken up by a trickle of cold rainwater in the night previously I can tell you that the main feature to look for in a bivi bag is waterproofing, and on paper the Hunka is no slouch, boasting a 10,000mm hydrostatic head and a “2.5 layer design”.  These decent stats come without substantial weight and have kept quite a few showers and many more heavy dews away from the Hunkas warm, dry, precious contents (me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/waterproof.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Even after being pushed about in my pack for a year, the waterproofing still hasn&#39;t faded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 3 season standard length and width Vango sleeping bag fits snugly in the Hunka with just enough fabric left to shield my face from rain.  The key to that perfect fit is the tapered profile which seems to have been thought out well and eliminates excess fabric and therefore excess weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slightly grippy inner surface of the Hunka coupled with the tailored style means that your sleeping bag and the Hunka move as one. This secure fit makes maneuvering back on to your sleeping pad in the night much less difficult and minimises the chance that your sleep-fidgeting will lead to a tangle, which means no freezing rain water spilling into your sleeping bag during the night as you sleep.  The tight fit will be an issue for bigger people or anyone hoping to use an inflatable sleeping pad and quilt, the Hunka XL which is slightly longer and wider will probably be the better choice there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/packed.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Although it packs down to a nice size in its incorporated stuff sack, it&#39;s much more useful as a dry bag or pack liner.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integral stuff sack on the footbox is a fantastic idea but the awkward ball shape formed by stuffing the Hunka into itself is actually inefficient to pack.  While ball mode is handy for long term storage, I usually use it as a dry bag for my clothes or tech while I’m hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British army Gore-Tex bivi bag is the closest real competitor in terms of price, at £30-40 on eBay it’s a steal, but then again at 800g it’s also a bit of a monster.  Gore-Tex, while definitely more windproof than the Hunka and probably more resistant to rips and tears definitely won’t pack down as neatly and is a noticeable weight in your backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bivi bag most frequently recommended to me has been the Snugpak special forces bivi, which looks similar to the Hunka but is constructed from Paratex and features a zip (why?!).  While is has been reviewed well and even comes recommended by Ray Mears, the extra weight and £75 price tag make choosing it over the Hunka unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there the prices only get more painful; with options like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/equipment-c3/tents-shelters-c25/bivi-bags-c41/survival-zone-lite-ultralight-bivi-bag-p120&quot;&gt;Rab Survival Zone or Survival Zone Light&lt;/a&gt; you get a 100g weight saving but you’re also chancing it with that 1,000mm hydrostatic head, and breaking the bank on the £110 price tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimal design of the Hunka overall is worth praise; there don’t need to be any grand designs with a bivi bag; it just needs to be light and waterproof, and that’s what you get here.  There are two drawcords which work well and the rest of the focus is on the vital part; the waterproof but breathable shell, all packed into a 360g package for less than £50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating 4/4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the price has sadly risen to £47 recently, the Hunka is still the best choice for anyone not ascending Everest.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/hunka-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/hunka-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>48 Hours: Wild Camping in Dartmoor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On the days approaching the Easter bank holiday weekend I knew I wanted to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; but could not settle on where to go or what to do. Fellow BoldlyGoer James suggested a few places but it was Dartmoor that really grabbed my attention. It is the only area in England where rights for wild camping are enshrined in the &lt;em&gt;National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act&lt;/em&gt;. Whilst not all of Dartmoor is covered by this, there are some pretty sizeable areas which allow wild camping (if you’re curious, have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0007/43909/vi-camping_map_309.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; map created by Dartmoor National Parks). After researching them on my 1:25k OS map for Dartmoor (OL28) I began to think about how my trip may go down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan unfolds in my mind… Drive down to Dartmoor on the Thursday, park up, hike and wild camp on the Thursday evening followed by a full day of walking on the Friday, wild camp that night and then hike back to the car on Saturday and drive back home. That’s about 48 hours. I decided that was short enough to carry all the supplies, food and water I would need for that time on my back, in my newly acquired &lt;em&gt;Osprey Atmos AG 65&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/1-pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pack, car and pack mule&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, due to the inevitable crash which always snarls up the M25 leading up to a bank holiday weekend I arrived in my planned starting point of Harford at about 7pm, a little later than planned. With sundown at around 8pm I made haste up into the hills to find a suitable spot to set up camp and have some dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/2-road.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Road to Harford&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just in time for sunset I reached Piles Hill and hunted for a flat spot to set up my tent. I thoroughly recommend this area or any of the surrounding hills for breathtaking views of Dartmoor at sunset and sunrise. It’s only about a 30 minute walk from the nearby (free) Harford car park too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/3-cairn.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Piles Hill Cairn&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I’d got the tent set up, the sun was just disappearing from view so I cracked out the gas stove, cooked up a Jamie Oliver &lt;em&gt;squeeze-out-the-bag&lt;/em&gt; dinner and scoffed it down. With darkness slowly crawling over the countryside and no desire to start a campfire, there really wasn’t much else to do but call it an early night and get some rest for a full day of hiking the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that this was my first experience of wild camping on my own. It’s a surreal experience to get used to; every sound outside of the tent amplified, making you question its origin. Even though I did have the internal reassurance that my wild camping pitch was entirely legal, it still didn’t stop me from imagining some wild beast, or worse, fellow camper, waking me in the night… Still, I got some kip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/4-camping.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Camping on Piles Hill (no pun required)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke early and decided to take a stroll, sans pack, to the nearby Ugborough Beacon which has stunning views out to Buckfastleigh and North Dartmoor. On arriving here I realised that this would also have been a fine spot to camp and would have offered a spectacular view of the sunrise, straight from the tent door!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/5-beacon.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Overlooking Ugborough Beacon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After walking back to my temporary abode, I packed up my gear and embarked on my way with the vague aim of striking camp somewhere North of Burrator Reservoir. Dartmoor offers some very decent paths if you stay on the beaten track and most of these run along the crest of the hills meaning that there is very little ascending and descending to be done. Dartmoor generally isn’t too hilly compared to our Lake and Peak District National Parks. The highest point in Dartmoor is High Willhays at 621m, way up in the top left corner; but the hills around the bottom part of Dartmoor are all below 500m. However, if you should stray from the beaten track, you may well be in for a calves aching exercise traversing the common grassy tufts. One of the most familiar sites along my trek were the famously furry, wild Dartmoor ponies; their tracks are littered across every path in Dartmoor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/6-ponies.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dartmoor ponies preparing to drop their seminal rap album&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another regular sight is sheep, their beady eyes staring until they’ve somehow decided you’re no longer a threat. I remember several times where a sheep was happily munching away on some foliage with its back to me when it would hear my footsteps and suddenly fly around to make eye contact. Dude, come on, I mean ewe no harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/7-pits.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Erme Pits (spot the ram)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my walk through Dartmoor I was greeted by a handful of people happily singing hello along with the question that demands to be answered by another question, lest, god forbid, you should strike up conversation…&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
   -   &lt;em&gt;“Hey! How’s it going?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   -   &lt;em&gt;“Hi, you alright?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did get talking to a couple of chaps out for a stroll from Ivybridge who informed me of a famous book about the area, &lt;em&gt;Dartmoor 365&lt;/em&gt; by John Hayward; named as such because there are approximately 365 square miles in Dartmoor. In this book, John details one specific site of interest in each of these square miles. My single serving friends also informed me that there is a lively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/296555273885240/&quot;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/a&gt; of people who go out of their way to photographically document as many of these 365 sites as possible. In my mind this is akin to geo-caching or a treasure hunt. After my excursion to Dartmoor, whilst sitting in the comfort of my own home, I requested entry to the group, was accepted, and proceeded to peruse some of the pictures posted in the group. I can proudly state that I have visited at least one of John Hayward’s 365 points of interest, Ditsworthy Warren, a rather spooky looking abandoned cottage near to Sheepstor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/8-warren.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ditsworthy Warren (totally not haunted)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ditsworthy Warren I headed to Sheepstor, skirting round Burrator Reservoir and up to Sharpitor aiming to find some camping spot with an epic view of the water but not too exposed to the elements. One risk with wild camping is that you’re constantly searching for that goldilocks spot… &lt;em&gt;“maybe the grass is greener on the other side of that hill…”&lt;/em&gt;.  Eventually I managed to convince myself that the spot I’d chosen was just right and made camp for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/9-gorse.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nestled in the Gorse&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After waking early again I planned my route back to the car whilst hearing a light pitter patter of rain on my tent. Ten minutes after setting off, fully kitted out in waterproofs, the light drizzle abated and I happily stuffed them back into my rucksack. At this point I was starting to feel slightly thankful that my supplies and water were dwindling; reducing the weight on my back and making it a less daunting task to tackle some more challenging obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/48dartmoor/10-planks.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When planning my route that morning I selected a circular route avoiding paths I’d already used. Included in this route was a path with an attractive straight section running south from Whiteworks. It was only after getting home, that I discovered that this stretch of land has a famous reputation. The path crosses over Foxtor Mires, a stinking bog, which is believed to be the inspiration for Grimpen Mire in Sir Arthur Conan Doyle’s classic, &lt;em&gt;The Hound of the Baskervilles&lt;/em&gt;. However, when I planned out my route, I didn’t realise its famous reputation. I didn’t even realise it was a bog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/11-mires.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Foxtor Mires&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Sir Arthur Conan Doyle brilliantly articulates the threatening nature of a bog and the truly terrible fate that could befall a man when he describes the demise of the villain, Mr Stapleton, in &lt;em&gt;Hound of the Baskervilles&lt;/em&gt; in his flight across the Grimpen Mire:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“There was no chance of finding footsteps in the mire, for the rising mud oozed swiftly in upon them, but as we at last reached firmer ground beyond the morass we all looked eagerly for them. But no slightest sign of them ever met our eyes. If the earth told a true story, then Stapleton never reached that island of refuge towards which he struggled through the fog upon that last night. Somewhere in the heart of the great Grimpen Mire, down in the foul slime of the huge morass which had sucked him in, this cold and cruel-hearted man is forever buried.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lost the path crossing through Foxtor Mires before the small bridge which takes you over the stream in its centre. I only found it after 20 minutes of wondering around that godforsaken bog trying to find a safe path, twice getting stuck up to my thighs. I think one of the most treacherous things about a bog is that it doesn’t look particularly threatening. A few tips from someone who has sunk in a bog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do a bog hop on the yellow tufts and keep moving, they’re more likely to take your weight, but not for long.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid any bright green mossy areas. This is where you will sink and you will get wet boots and maybe a wet bum.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a walking stick to probe suspicious patches in front.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t cross a bog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/12-bog.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;I smell like bog&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another three hours of walking with wet boots I reached the car, exhausted but satisfied with a couple of days well spent exploring one of our country’s best national parks. Still I was happy to get back into some warm (and dry) clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/13-done.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Done&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/wild-camping-dartmoor</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/wild-camping-dartmoor</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trangia 28-T Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Inexpensive&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Light pans&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small form factor&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Heavy burner&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my mini Trangia 28-T for £18 from outdoorgear.co.uk in May 2016.  The neat stacking design, coupled with the low weight and price made the 28 stand out from the crowd straight away.  After dozens of overnighters and a few weekend trips I need to make some changes to save weight, but my cooking experience has been overwhelmingly positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pot, pot stand and frying pan are made from aluminium with the burner constructed from brass and the handle a lightweight alloy.  The aluminium construction means a slight drop in durability over some titanium counterparts, but the reduction in price and similar weight more than makes up for that in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aluminium pot is immediately recognisable as the design as featured in the larger Trangias which have become famous for standing up to all of the bumps and scrapes that occur in outdoor life.  I have seen several trodden on or sat on, bent completely out of shape, before being pushed back into a rough circle and chucked back on the fire.  Having used my mini pot on gas, alcohol and coals, I have no doubt that this smaller Trangia will stand up to the same punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frying pan is aluminium coated with non-stick coating which looks and feels quite fragile.  Trangia provide you with a sheet of thin plastic to protect the coating from the sharp edges of the pot stand and handle stored inside, this hasn’t stopped chipping where the pan clips over the lip of the pot.  Perhaps more of a design flaw than a quality issue, it is rather annoying and now it is chipped it will only get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burner, pot stand and handle are all solidly constructed; the burner and simmer ring fit together in a satisfyingly snug way; the handle, while flimsy, is actually surprisingly resilient and doesn’t buckle even when the pot is full of water; and the pot stand provides a rigid base for stirring and mixing over heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/handle.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Although it doesn&#39;t look like much, the handle is much easier to grip than the one in the Trangia 25 or 27.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first feature that stood out to me was the tiny form factor of the packed 28.  Everything fits neatly inside the systems pot with the frying pan over the top holding all of the components securely in place with room enough for teabags and 4 or 5 porridge packets to spare.  Being able to pick up one 15cm x 6.5cm item and know that you have packed your entire cookset in one go is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slimmed-down 0.8 litre pot of the mini coupled with the same brass burner as a larger Trangia leads to a much improved boil time, in my experience it takes around 6-7 minutes to boil 1 litre of water.  This reduced capacity has also allowed for a slimmer handle design which eliminates the chance of miss-gripping the pot rim and dropping it, which I used to do a lot with the old design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/overview.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some complain about the lack of a handle for the simmer ring, but you can slide it quite easily if you are careful and lift it slightly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only item which hasn’t changed in design from the larger Trangias is the burner itself.  It provides a stable temperature, doesn’t spit at all and the rubber-lined cap stops alcohol leaking through your backpack, but at 115g it makes up more than a third of the total weight.  I am definitely going to swap the burner out for a homemade coke can stove in the near future and probably leave the frying pan at home too which will reduce the weight to ~200g.  But if I’m changing the burner, leaving the pan (and lid) at home, why bother with the rest of it at all? Why not just buy a pot separately and make a stove to begin with? Well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market for alcohol stoves is limited.  It essentially boils down to Trangia burners, designs that look a lot like Trangia design knock offs, or simple stoves made from cans which seem expensive given that you could make them yourself for next to nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go ultralight straight away and have a tight-ish budget, I have only heard good things about  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.storminstovesystems.co.uk/&quot;&gt;stormin stove system&lt;/a&gt; at roughly £20 and 68g.  Paired with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alpkit.com/products/mytipot&quot;&gt;Mytipot&lt;/a&gt; which is £29 and weighs 94g and a homemade can stove you can achieve a system weighing just under 200g for £49.  But hold on, we already had this with the 28 if you leave the frying pan at home and swap out the stove, all for only £24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try a knock off Trangia design &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/NuoYa005-Solid-liquid-Alcohol-Cooking-Backpacking/dp/B00HBMOSJY/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/SZCXTOP-Portable-Alcohol-Aluminium-Backpacking/dp/B01N56JS2T/ref=sr_1_7?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-7&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Tatonka-Stainless-Steel-Alcohol-Burner-x/dp/B000G4XIA4/ref=sr_1_8?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-8&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;.
The ones I have seen weigh up to 100g more than the 28 burner and pot stand, and once you factor in the cost of a pot too they aren’t much cheaper, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, unless you make your own can stove, chicken wire pot stand, tinfoil wind guard and repurpose an aluminium mess tin as your pot, it’s going to be very hard indeed to find a system as light and functional as the 28-T for anywhere near the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/cooking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Whether you need to stop for a quick brew or cook a major meal for one or two, the 28-T can hack it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I opened my bottle of meths for my inaugural meal with the 28 I was struck with flashbacks to my scouting days.  Stuck on the side of a hill in darkness, three people around a Trangia 25, bodies positioned awkwardly in an attempt to shield the flame from the wind, hungry tempers flaring as pasta floating in a litre of water began to simmer lazily after more than 15 minutes of waiting.  I realised I may have made a huge mistake investing in another product from the same designers but a few meals in I realised most of my fears were misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For less money than a single titanium pot you get a complete, convenient, collapsible system.  Most of the components of the system are handy to have around to use on their own; the pot and handle do well on a gas stove, the stand and pot do well on their own with a different burner, the pot alone cooks on an open fire, the handle fits any pot with a lip.  It’s one of those kits that is so versatile at least one piece of it will end creeping its way into your pack wherever you are heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating 4/4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 28 makes for a brilliant starting stove for a new solo backpacker or a decent ultralight option if you swap out the burner, all for less than the price of a single titanium cooking pot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/trangia-28t-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/trangia-28t-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
