<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BOLDLY GOES</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 23:09:06 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 23:09:06 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photo Story: Coast to Coast Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-was-the-best-of-times-it-was-the-blurst-of-times&quot;&gt;1. It was the Best of Times, it was the Blurst of Times&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Sam and me at the beginning of the coast to coast walk in St. Bees, a minor village on the west coast of Cumbria. Above us is a profile map of the route, an abstract squiggle to most, but for those who’ve walked the 192 mile route across England it is an unforgettable reminder of the ups and downs the path brings. I squiggled all over this photo from the comfort of a Youth Hostel bed at the Whitby priory having *almost finished the epic walk. It speaks of my state of mind at the end of this journey: there were a number of challenging parts to this trip that nearly scuppered us completely, on the other hand, there were apparently only three vaguely remembered ‘stupidly good views’ and no other positive moments of note? Surely there was more to it than that? Surely we didn’t just suffer for 192 miles walking for nothing? Surely?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-route&quot;&gt;2. The Route&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The route that Alfred Wainwright put together takes you across the entirety of the Lake District, the Pennines, the Vale of York, and lastly, the North York Moors. Although well trodden and very well known, Alf’s Coast to Coast route is not a national path and is therefore not signposted particularly consistently. Navigational skills are in fact required. Cicerone do make a booklet with excerpts of the pertinent segments of the 10 or-so OS maps that cover the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;humble-beginnings&quot;&gt;3. Humble Beginnings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning there were four. Harvey and Tom had joined Sam and me for the first couple of days of the walk, walking from St. Bees to Grasmere (Grazmere?/Grarsemere?). We had caught the train at the crack of dawn up to Leeds, where we denied a pint at 8.54am and were told to return in six minutes. Wetherspoons: I actually think I’m surprised. We then took the beautiful journey from Leeds to Carlisle and then the rickety one from Carlisle to St. Bees. We arrived in St.Bees by 3pm and were eager to crack on. We dipped our toes in the very edge of the wild and foreboding Irish Sea (even paddling would have been genuinely life threatening) and set off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From St.Bees the path takes you along high red sandstone cliffs, leading towards the lighthouse which marks the most western tip of Cumbria. The elements had treated us to beautiful blue skies with one hand but whipped us with a hard wind with the other. I followed the others, filled with anticipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first foot steps of an adventure fill me with thoughts of excitement as well as doubt. I wondered, privately, whether fate would break our stride; whether my ankle would hold out, or whether I’d be able keep up with the others. At the same time I was glad to finally be there on the path, having looked forward to it for so long. I have learned to appreciate that these steps are, in one respect, among the hardest of all: it’s easy to dream of adventures, and equally easy to put them off, ‘until next summer’, ‘until I have the savings’, ‘until I have the time’, ‘until x,y, and z’. A plethora of practicalities stand between us and the realisation of our ambitions. Indeed, finding yourself making first step on your adventure symbolises that half the battle is already won. The worries of everyday life can’t stop you now, from the beginning of the journey to its end, your only challenge is keep moving towards your goal, one foot in front of the other. Here we were, we’d finally made it, we’d planned, prepared, planned some more and at last set off on a grand adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-pieces-of-advice&quot;&gt;4. Three Pieces of Advice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do bring Sudocrem, or some such like, for alleviating chafing after a long day’s hike.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do bring a small bottle of hot sauce to pep up bland trail meals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not allow hot sauce to get on hands prior to applying sudocrem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough said? Enough said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-trials-and-tribulations-of-day-two&quot;&gt;The Trials and Tribulations of Day Two&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had wild camped just on the edge of the Lake District on our first night. Where once the hills had loomed in the distance, the morning light of our second day had revealed the hills right before us. We were to head past England’s most remote youth hostel at Black Sail (which we visited back in May). We even caught up with the Warden there: James, who is a man of legendary levels of safeness. We will meet again, James! From there, we climbed up and out of the Ennerdale valley, to Honister pass, bypassing the standard stop at Rosthwaite and heading instead up Greenup Gill, past the memorial for Gordon Hallworth, towards Grasmere, where we’d say goodbye to Tom and Harvey and say hello to Chris, who was to join us for the remainder of the walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was to be one of those hikes that would get the better of us. In the final hours of our walk a dour rain had begun to fall our and energy levels had depleted in the content neglect of knowing there was not much further to go. We did have plenty of food with us, mostly in the form of the solid rocket boosters that are PB+J wraps (which will get you up a mountain if you can stomach them). We dodged then waded, pathless, through the bog at the top of Greenup Edge, whereby we caught our first glimpse of Chris, or at least what we thought might be Chris. A tiny speck in the valley beneath us, moving slowly along the path. I wolf-whistled, and the figure paused, scanned around the mountain side and continued moving. Had he heard us? We trudged down the path, (myself, certainly) growing increasingly grouchy in our eighteenth mile of the day. Eventually, and luckily, we found Chris, who had already scouted out a spot to camp, ‘it’s just up this small hill’, I nearly collapsed in protest at the thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell into my tent once I’d shonkily put it up, chowed down on some highly fragrant Chorizo and then promptly passed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I awoke, glad that our most arduous day was behind us, outside my tent I could hear footsteps. I unzipped the door to see Sam pacing. I asked him for the time, to which he answered ‘it’s about half-past bleeeuurrrghh’, Sam had spewed a great stream of steaming brown chunder mid sentence. I slowly zipped up my tent door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-sickness-and-in-health&quot;&gt;6. In Sickness and in Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached Grasmere early that morning and gathered around a cafe table in the rain. Harvey and Tom were about to depart on a bus and Sam was still very unwell. Sam considered calling it a day and heading for home too. I, however, wouldn’t have it. we’d planned to do this trip for months and I knew it would have eaten away at Sam if he had returned home so early in the trip. We instead booked ourselves into the youth hostel where we could wait for Sam’s sickness to pass. I must admit I was worried about him, and hoped that I’d done the right thing in urging him not to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom and Harvey had said their goodbyes and Chris, Sam and I headed to the hostel. We soon found ourselves plonked in a pleasingly over-warm lounge, blearily lazing about, no doubt making the place look bad. Sam caught up with some much needed sleep whilst Chris and I explored the mish mash of books on the bookshelf. I learned a lot about the history of the Silk Road that day. Then, as the evening drew in, a feeling of impending doom came over me. ‘Uh-oh’, I thought to myself. ‘Nausea!’, I exclaimed. Chris concurred that this was indeed a word of Greek origin (as we were mid talk about words derived from Latin and Greek, of which he is an expert), ‘No,’ I replied, ‘I’m feeling nauseous!’. Chris kindly reassured me and attempted to distract me but it was no-dice. This was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had suffered the same fate as Sam, some mystery bug had got the better of both of us. We were to spend another night in Grasmere, this time waiting for me to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-the-road-again&quot;&gt;7. On the Road Again&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having been stuck in Grasmere purgatory for 2 days, 3 for Chris, it was a welcome feeling to be on the trail again. As I look back in my memory, this day’s walking for me was my favourite of all. We hiked up-and-over towards Patterdale, and then made the reasonably steady ascent to Kidsty Pike, the highest point of our trip standing at 780m, not huge but still not to be sniffed at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lake’s were at their best this day, more beautiful than I’ve ever seen them before. One thing you notice here is that you can spend hours looking upon the same hillsides, and then as you reach a summit, your vista is in seconds completely transformed, each time as if you’ve found a new world. As you reach the top of Kidsty, and catch sight of the land that lies beyond it, your horizons are suddenly incredibly distant as the rugged, edged hills of Cumbria relent into the porous limestone plateaus that stretch all the way to Nine Standards Rigg beyond Kirkby Stephen some 30 miles away. It was bloody lovely, it was. But we couldn’t hang about, night was drawing in and we needed find a good spot to camp, so we sloshed our way down the hill towards Haweswater and set about looking a spot to pitch-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;five-star-wild-camping&quot;&gt;8. Five Star Wild Camping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s this? A walled grove of trees with a stone firepit? I had ran up ahead to have a quick look to see if there was a decent place to pitch up for the night. Within 30 seconds I’d gestured back with a thumbs up to the others. Sometimes a wild camp spot can end up being a bit of a ‘this will have to do’ situation; with uneven ground, not very out of sight, trespassing etc. But this wasn’t the case here. This was five star wild camping, every criteria for a great spot was met and more. Ok maybe there were a lot of midges now I think of it, but I’m willing to look past this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;honesty-and-generosity&quot;&gt;9. Honesty and Generosity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The occasional trove of goodies such as this appear throughout the journey. They are great and I like them very much. Thanks Thomas Richardson! This particular box of goodies can be found on the eastern side of Naddle Bridge a few miles from Shap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-swaledales-to-texels&quot;&gt;10. From Swaledale’s to Texel’s&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest joys of walking long distance is seeing the landscape around you gradually changing. Having hiked out of the Lake District along the shores of Haweswater reservoir we found ourselves in a completely different environment. Most noticeably, the land was much flatter, and much drier and dotted with lots of natural springs bubbling out of limestone cracks. There were other differences too, for example, we began to notice that Sheep had changed from the haggard and ugly Swaledale’s you find psyching you out halfway up any given fell, chewing gormlessly as you pant your way slowly up the hillside, and given way to much more daft looking Texel Sheep with their squashed faces that look quite cheerful in their ignorance of what’s in store for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d passed by Shap which was teeming with people taking part in one of these self-flagellating uber-marathons that have added cargo nets, walls, and spike pits (probably). We spent a good while watching them, a good way to pass time as we rested up. For it was to be one of those days where the pit-stops were all made in record time, each lasting longer than the last. Tiredness was again playing its part, and towards the end of the day and we wound up camping where our legs finally gave in. Luckily this happened to be on the high side of a broad valley overlooking the northern end of the Yorkshire Dales which were draped in the orange light of the setting sun and followed by the silver light of a full moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/c2c1/15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the next part of our Coast to Coast adventure…..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/c2c-part-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/c2c-part-1</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Q&amp;A with Ray Mears</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ray Mears needs no introduction. We are all familiar with his superb TV programmes and books from over the years covering survival, bushcraft, history, and even foraging. This Autumn Ray will be touring the UK with his show ‘Born To Go Wild’, which your can find out more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.raymears.com/2017/02/15/ray-mears-tour-dates-for-2017-born-to-go-wild/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here at Boldy Goes we were particularly excited when we heard about Ray’s tour and thought we’d catch up with him before he hits the road later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray has been a pivotal figure in laying down the foundations for us ultimately making this website dedicated to bringing stories of adventures in the wilder corners of Britain, and further afield. We met the opportunity of talking with Ray with all the zeal of your quintessential ‘Trekkie’, or a ‘Trackie’ perhaps?……..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray Mears Born To Go Wild will be at theatres around the UK from 8 October 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.raymears.com/2017/02/15/ray-mears-tour-dates-for-2017-born-to-go-wild/&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;You can check the tour dates and book here now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few questions we put to Ray when we spoke to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boldy Goes: I remember your TV series ‘Wild Food’ fondly, I did notice however, that your co-presenter Professor Gordon Hill, never seemed to enjoy the food eaten on the show as much as you did. What, if ever, has been enough to induce from you a Hill-esque grimace upon eating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ray Mears&lt;/strong&gt;: Gordon was wonderful to work with, I have many fond memories of experimental wild food meals that we tried some successful and a few others not so successful. There have been a few things that have made me grimace, the sight of a toredo worm being the most memorable, a long slimy insipid white worm like mollusc that bores into ships timbers and dead mangrove trees. Strangely enough it tasted deliciously like crab sandwich spread with a hint of chilli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/raymears/ray_mears_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you excited about right now? And what’s next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited about being home planning future projects, enjoying being home with my wife and being out in the glorious British countryside. Right now I am preparing for the Born to go Wild tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your new UK tour, Born to go Wild runs from 8th October through to the end of November and travels all around the country. Would you be able to talk a little bit about what we can expect from the show?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, in the first half I am going to talk about and demonstrate skills particularly fire skills exploring why it has been important to humanity and what it still means in really wild places. In the second half I will explore the importance of watching and learning about wild life, with examples from recent filming expeditions in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve travelled the world, seen it in its most extreme and hostile forms and have been to our planet’s pockets of paradise. Where is your favourite place to visit time and again? Where is a place you don’t want to return to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is really hard to single out one particular place there are so many and so very varied. Certainly Canada, Australia and Africa have called me back many times but equally there are the remote islands of the pacific or the country trails of the U.S.A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While outside you often allude to the “inner silence” you find while becoming part of the forest. You have gleaned many technical skills from bushcraft masters all over the globe, but who are your biggest influences on the spiritual side of being outdoors?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a really difficult question, I have encountered many varied spiritual perspectives on life. Personally, I would say I have found the strongest connection with many of the spiritual beliefs demonstrated by the First Nations in Canada and the United States, although what I have learned from my visits with Australian Aboriginal communities has been fascinating and mind expanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/raymears/ray_mears_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you make a programme who are you trying to please?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I make a film with aboriginal people, they are my target audience. I want them to be happy with the way they are represented on screen. I was once stopped by an Inuit man in Yellowknife Canada. He recognised me from the TV and said, ‘I like your programmes they tell things how they really are.’ It was the best praise I have ever received, he then went on to share a skill of fire making in the tundra with me that was of immense benefit just a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you know that you were/are my childhood hero? Without your TV shows and books my life and experiences would have been much less rich. Not really a question, I just wanted to say thanks!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can the Boldly Goes boys and I come camping with you sometime?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes please do, let’s plan something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray Mears Born To Go Wild will be at theatres around the UK from 8 October, 
you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.raymears.com/2017/02/15/ray-mears-tour-dates-for-2017-born-to-go-wild/&quot;&gt;check the tour dates and book here now!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/ray-mears</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/ray-mears</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Managing Diabetes in the mountains</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a walker and have been since I can remember. From tottering up the bottom section of the Watkin path on Snowdon at age two, to organising a three-day trek in Snowdonia at age fifteen, I have always felt at home exploring the mountains. By my early thirties I had walked extensively in Snowdonia as well completing hikes in the Lake District, Peak District and Scotland. I have a kind of obsession with Snowdon and have summited forty-two times by a number of different route combinations. Hiking and scrambling have always been my escape. When life gets tough, I run away to the mountains and am always renewed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/managing/managing_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, last year, I got really ill. I was rapidly losing weight and became so weak that the most basic everyday activity became extremely difficult. I would drop things and regularly lost my balance when walking. My eyesight also began to deteriorate. There were other symptoms too, which I shall not go into detail here. I was in denial. For months, my situation worsened, but who wants to admit the fact that there may be something seriously wrong? I explained it away in my head. It must be work. I was a new teacher and extreme tiredness is par for the course in this profession. I eventually saw a doctor who, after testing my blood glucose level, told me I had to go to hospital immediately. That night I was diagnosed with Type 1 Diabetes and kept in overnight on an insulin drip. On release, my condition did not improve as expected and, to cut a long story short, I was diagnosed with Pernicious Anaemia, Hypothyroidism and Polycythaemia over the next few months. The latter three conditions are all easily treated with injections and prescription drugs, but Diabetes is a life-changer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diabetes management is a complex thing and can be overwhelming to start with. I wondered if I would ever be able to hike again. In Type 1 Diabetes the body is not able to produce its own insulin. Insulin is a hormone that basically transports glucose from your blood into your cells for energy. As the body is no longer able to regulate blood glucose levels, this must be done ‘manually’. This is the tricky bit. If blood glucose rises too high it results in hyperglycaemia, which if occurs too frequently over an extended period of time, leads to all sorts of scary complications such as blindness, kidney failure, heart failure, nervous system failure, basically ‘everything failure’. Low blood glucose, hypoglycaemia, if untreated, leads to diabetic coma and death. The difficulty in keeping blood glucose levels within an acceptable range is that there are so many factors that influence it. Generally speaking, carbohydrates raise blood glucose and insulin lowers it. Exercise is a big factor too and it was this that was the biggest concern for me. Exercise dramatically lowers blood glucose levels and can easily lead to hypoglycaemia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diabetes however would not beat me. Steve Redgrave, diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes at age 35, said: “Diabetes has to live with me, not me live with it”. I took inspiration from this and from other professional sports people with the condition. Progress was slow. During my early recovery period, I would walk one mile in the field behind my home, slowly. I would work out how many Jelly Babies I needed to compensate for the energy expended. One Jelly Baby has five grams of carbohydrates and would allow me to walk for fifteen minutes without my blood glucose dropping too far. I wondered what people might think seeing a man out walking for exercise and replacing the calories expended immediately by eating sweets as he walked!  In time, I extended my walk to two miles and switched the Jelly Babies for snacks with a lower glycaemic index (slower conversion from carbohydrates to glucose). I became more confident and the fear lessened the more I experimented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months after diagnosis I decided to go big. Snowdon was waiting. But I needed to be careful. This was a big step (I’ve never been a very patient person). There was no chance I would be doing this on my own so I recruited my two brothers, both experienced hikers. I chose a route that neither of them had done before, ‘The Rollercoaster’. A 10-hour walk involving five peaks and a lot of up and down in between. As well as the usual map, waterproofs, spare fleece and water, my pack this time (and ever since) included a lot of carbohydrate snacks, glucose tablets and glucose test strips. Blood glucose levels were checked at least every hour and carbohydrates regularly eaten. On a few occasions, blood glucose dropped a bit low and glucose tablets were required but overall, the diabetes was managed and the trip was successful. I could even justify a very unhealthy feast in the summit café. Energy levels were good throughout and the future was now brighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/managing/managing_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since diagnosis seventeen months ago, I have completed eighteen peaks in the UK and a winter hike on the lower slopes of the Eiger North Face. There are still challenges. My blood glucose monitor does not work in sub-zero temperatures during winter walks and diabetes changes during the early years, so treatment routines need to be adjusted. I continue to be inspired by others with the condition. In 2015 a guy named Jerry Gore, a type 1 diabetic in his fifties, made a speed ascent of the north face of the Eiger, still one of the most dangerous climbs around. Fortunately, I still have my escape. I can go to the mountains and with some additional care, can wander to my heart’s content.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/managing-diabetes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/managing-diabetes</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hiking the GR20</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The GR20 is 180km, and when Googled is described as ‘the toughest long distance trail in Europe’. Starting in the northwest of Corsica and running over the mountainous spine of the island, and ending in the southeast. There are dozens of GR (or Grande Randonnée) footpaths all over France, Spain, and other parts of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew none of this when asked if I would like to accompany my friend Neil on the trail. We were on a caving expedition in the Austrian Alps. He was about to embark on a five-day underground camp, but was already thinking about his next adventure. I’d been in the mountains of the Picos De Europa in Northern Spain the month before, so felt fairly fit. Neil had spent the past month climbing at altitude in France and Switzerland, but I might be able to just about keep up. He had no one to hike with anyway and I had nothing planned when back in the UK, so thought why not? I’d not hiked two days in a row since the Duke of Edinburgh weekend in Derbyshire aged thirteen, but how hard could it be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I booked my flights, slightly concerned that we seemed to have only allowed for twelve days hiking, when most people took 15 to 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A lady kindly let us shelter under her porch during a storm. She even brought us coffee out!
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instigating impromptu parties the night before sleeping on the floor of Gatwick Airport about to hike across an entire country is NOT recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Putting your new tent up for the first time, in a thunderstorm, only to discover the poles supplied are for a tent twice its size, is a bad idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wearing short shorts makes it remarkably easy to hitch a ride to the start of the trail.  The locals are friendly and happy to help anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from day 1 camp.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first day’s hiking went well- the terrain was steep but not technical and our campsite had an excellent view. I’d brought a tiny 2/3 length inflatable matt that was dismissed on site as a poor choice. I however viewed it as a good one when Neil was forced to wake up each night to re-inflate his cushy thick roll matt that turned out to have a slow puncture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought to get a head start on the first uphill section of day two, and do it in the cool of the morning. We set off at an alarmingly early 6am, headtorches on. Unfortunately, what is relatively easy navigation in daylight- simply look for the red and white painted markers- becomes much harder before the sun has risen. After several false trails and backtracks, it was decided that the extra hours sleep made much more sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The northern half of the GR20 is predominantly steep rocky paths, boulder hopping, and scrambling. Technical but fun, and making one very grateful for walking poles. Corsica is gorgeous, and from up high you get at least one glimpse of the sea most days. This does however give the impression of not getting anywhere fast- why can we still see it?? There are many beautiful clear rivers and streams running through the mountains. We were using chlorine tablets, but the locals seemed to just drink straight from the stream. After a hot sweaty day we washed our clothes and ourselves in the river by our camp. It felt great but it’s debatable what’s better: clothes that smell of sweat or clothes that smell of sweat and river water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We quickly picked up a routine. You cultivate a very particular way of setting up your sleeping area, the order things are done in, who does which task. Up at 6 (6:30 if we’re honest), munch down two bland packaged pain au chocolat, get out of your one set of sleeping clothes, into your one (and increasingly smelly) set of walking clothes. Brace for getting out of the cosy sleeping bag and pack up camp as fast as possible. We’d generally stop for lunch about 12, then push on to the next night’s camp site for 2-5pm, depending on how long that leg was. We made great time on the uphill sections. Unfortunately a year-old skiing injury to my knee made the downhill painful and relatively slow going, but we were still on course for our time limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food situation was expectedly monotonous. Either smash, pasta, or couscous, with tuna (not good) or chorizo (much better), a carrot, and  stock cubes. Followed by  two chocolate biscuits each. Lunch was bread and cheese. Unfortunately the Corsicans are fond of a very strong, (and very expensive when up at mountain huts) goat’s cheese. It feels particularly sad to be forcing down something that tastes awful, that you know cost you 15 euros, but you need the calories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of the steep bits of rock have chains on to help pull yourself up, others don’t.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the midpoint of Vizzavona at the end of day 6. The village there is tiny, but felt strange after being out of civilization even for such a short time. We took a day off to catch the train to Corte for a break and to restock on food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on we continued, knowing the southern half of the trail was meant to be easier, or at least slightly less rugged and mountainous. Though by that time I had stopped thinking ‘just got to get to the top of that hill’. It’s pointless when you know there will just be another one after it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t take long to really miss life’s little luxuries. You don’t realise the joy of sitting on a clean toilet until you and your walking companion both have dodgy stomachs; waiting your turn for the trowel and rationing the last of the loo roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few days were spent counting down: one day down, loads still to go; two days down, loads still to go. As the end drew nearer I became more focused on the stunning scenery and appreciated the simplicity of just walking each day. I would take my turn on the kindle each evening for half an hour, then be asleep before nine, Neil not much further behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part of the southern half was the shortage of water points. There was a night where we went to sleep thirsty, having to ration our water, woke up thirsty, then hiked a couple of hours uphill and in the heat of the sun before we found a dribble running down the rock. Luckily we had a filter straw so took turns sucking up moisture, not bothering to stop for breath. Thirst definitely brought me to my grumpiest. I began fantasising about an ice cold Orangina for hours on end. The final day was a draught day. The last village we’d been in we had taken turns going to the shop and buying a ‘luxury’ item. Neil chose Haribo. I chose a big ripe pear each, for which Neil mocked me. But on that final day when we had no water and the sun was creating an oven out of the valley, that pear was the juiciest, best pear I’ve ever eaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Neil sucking water from a rock.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the GR20 is fairly anticlimactic. You end up in a small, not very attractive town. But we were happy to be done nonetheless. Ten and a bit days of hiking brought us in well under guidebook time. We had met one of the managers of a mountain hut and discovered that he ran it in three days, but we were still pretty pleased. It’s definitely inspired me to look for another long distance trail to take up. We met a couple out there who were planning the PCT, maybe one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting round the pool at our fancy main town campsite the night before our flight, another friend messaged me asking why I wasn’t coming up to Skye the next day. I needed a rest, but the adventure bug was still biting so I booked a connecting flight to Glasgow then and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lessons learnt: Take more than one loo roll between two people, for two weeks. A needle and thread is very handy for stitching together broken tents. It’s a great way to lose weight, I’ve never seen so many of my ribs! And grab every opportunity that presents itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_9.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gr20/corsica_10.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All photos taken by Neil Cox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/GR-20</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/GR-20</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A wild tea tasting session</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hiding in plain sight along every hedge row in England is an underutilised wealth of flavour.  Each year from late July to September a separate crop of “weeds” ripens in the gaps between fields of corn and peas and rots on the vine, almost entirely ignored both by farmers and the general population.  Most people are not even aware that the fruit exists and some who are are put off by the thought that foraging near fields might be seen as stealing, but actually as long as you are picking for personal consumption you are protected by the law in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
&quot;A person who picks mushrooms growing wild on any land, or who picks flowers, fruit or foliage from a plant growing wild on any land, does not (although not in possession of the land) steal what he picks, unless he does it for reward or for sale or other commercial purpose.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - The England and Wales Theft Act 1968&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer, James and I decided to spend some time searching for and tasting some hedgerow delicacies, we were pleasantly surprised by what we found in a very short space of time.  We started with the more common forageable plants and chose tea as the medium by which to explore the flavours as it is easily prepared with the most basic camping equipment, requires no extra ingredients and no messy preparation or clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We prepared each tea in the same way; by simply adding the foraged item to hot water, sometimes lightly crushing or tearing it first so that brewed faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began with Blackberries, these sweet fruits are easily spotted on brambles all over the country and are tasty straight off of the plant.  Brewing a handful in to two cups of hot water provides a sweet and light flavour with an aftertaste dominated by tannins which stays with you for some time and really wakes you up.  Brewed with more berries, the sugars override the astringent aftertaste and make something we really recommend, especially when you are cold and need a pick-me-up in the woods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wildteas/blackberry.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sweet and slightly tangy, it would be most welcome on a cold morning or once left to cool, enjoyed as a cordial on a summer&#39;s day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we picked some leaves from a Hawthorn bush, tore them up and added them with a few seeded berries to boiling water.  This tea did not smell particularly appetising and tasted about the same, quite earthy, bitter but with some of the apple-y notes that the leaves provide when chewed raw.   I took some of the berries home and dried them above my boiler; the dried berries made for a much sweeter tea, but it wasn’t really worth the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final and surprisingly palatable tea came from the abundant wild spearmint supply in the meadow the other side of the hedgerow.  We expected to taste mint straight away, but there is actually a sweet and aromatic tangy flavour more like celery first, followed by an airy spearmint aftertaste.  We would definitely recommend this tea, mostly because it is so easy to prepare and tastes incredible, but also because it always seems to grow in the best sunny spots in meadows covered in butterflies and bumblebees.  After all, the best foraging brings you to a new beautiful place physically as well as culinarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wildteas/spearmint.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The spearmint tea left us with a refreshed feeling and a hankering for a &lt;i&gt;Polo&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you start looking for tasty treats in the undergrowth a foraging Baader-Meinhof effect kicks in quite quickly, soon you’ll be spotting food in places you have driven past every day for years and begin wondering why no-one else has noticed this before.  We picked everything we needed to make these teas and more from a single hedgerow on one side of a field in Hertfordshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wildteas/tea.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I am fully prepared and have been on the lookout for flowers and other tell tale signs of a soon-to-be ripening feast in some hedges and trees while running.  I have marked several spots I think are developing well on my OS map and plan to bring you some more tasting sessions and recipe ideas later in the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember not to over do it with any foraged fruit and plants, not only because you should leave some for the local wildlife and re-seeding for next year, but also because some foraged fruits contain chemicals that can be both beneficial and detrimental to your health.  If you have any ongoing medical conditions check with a doctor before you try some of these teas!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/wild-teas</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/wild-teas</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 hours in the Peak District: Summer Solstice Camp</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/peakdistrict/cave_view.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the night drew gently in, a string of red lights lit up, reaching one by one higher into the sky. The transmitting station at Holme Moss stands as-the-crow-flies only 3 miles away from our camp spot high up on the side of Laddow Rocks, a rocky outcrop at the northern end of the Peak District. Further away to the east, the headlights of cars passing across the top of Langsett Moor streamed around the meandering bends of the A628. An Airbus A380 passed overhead, bound for Manchester. Yet, as is so often the case for those wild camping, we had somehow found ourselves a small pocket of wilderness; a bastion within a land of creeping bricks and tarmac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/1_valley.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the day of the summer solstice when we drove from Hertfordshire up the M1 and into the peaks, passing Chesterfield’s crooked and twisted church spire, looking like some elaborate set for a movie. We took a diversion to stop at Alpkit’s new flagship store at Hathersage where we picked up a couple of bits of new kit, namely the Alpkit Numo and a new Sawyer water filter, which we will be reviewing in the coming weeks. The shop, by the way, is very cool, and well worth the visit if you’re into your camping and hiking. I have to say their tents look excellent in the flesh and made a much more resounding impression with me and Sam in store than they had done on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/2_river.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made our purchases and hit the road, heading towards Crowden where we parked the car and made the 3 mile hike up to the Laddow rocks. The first part of our hike was done under a cloudless sky, the sheep had retreated from their pastures and were lazing beneath the few copses of trees that lined the path. Thankfully, as our path began to get steeper the clouds rolled in, offering some respite from the searing heat. A large bird of prey flew past, barely using its wings as it soared over us. We ruled out the usual suspects, too slender to be a Buzzard, too large for a Sparrowhawk and certainly not a Red Kite. Perhaps a Hen Harrier, maybe even a Montagu’s?  We steadily reached the top of the crags of Laddow Rocks and it was time to start scouting for our spot: a small sheltered cave on the face of the crags used mostly by climbers. We had learned of the spot from a Reddit post and quickly put it on the list of places we wanted to go. It was hard to get any specific details about how to find the spot and it was up to us to keep our eyes peeled for a likely looking path to get to the cave. Fortunately we found the route down to the cave without too much difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/3_cave.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is just enough room in the cave for two people to camp in and there are a number of rocks and ledges that make for good seats and cubby holes for putting your gear. All in all a very cozy spot with an amazing view of the valley below, and best of all completely free! We had worried on the journey about the possibility that some other equally enlightened wild campers may already have nabbed the cave for themselves but luckily there was no sign of any other people when we arrived (in fact, in our whole trip we only saw two other people) apart from a silver plastic bag secured under a rock in the cave. Inside was a small blue visitor’s book and a biro, I opened it up to read the entries to find that we were the first people to find the book and the only other entry was written by the person that left the notebook behind just a few days prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/4_clouds.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heat wave was passing and in its wake came the storm clouds, the sky was rich with orange and yellow hued clouds, towering up like distant rugged mountain ranges. We were well sheltered by the rocks as we watched the weather draw in. This was it, the circled day on the calendar, the summer solstice, a wonderful time to be camping and enjoying the long days and short, never-quite-dark nights. This camp also marked the antithesis of the night we had spent on the Norfolk coast last December, on the winter solstice, which you can read about &lt;a href=&quot;/features/24-norfolk&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where the inky night was heavy presence that defined the experience, an experience seldom had in the age of electric light. But tonight symbolised the summer, a time when our environment is at its most forgiving and bountiful, a time which has been celebrated by the peoples of Britain for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written of having a digital detox &lt;a href=&quot;/features/soloventures&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, where I proclaim that taking 24 hours to switch off from the hyperconnectivity of modern life is a refreshing and revitalizing experience and something I would highly recommend to anyone and everyone to try at least once. Camping on the face of a cliff in the Peak District is perhaps the epitome of this notion. And I felt that in this time of division and uncertainty in Britain, a time that has been testing my faith in this country and the people who run it, just spending some time outside at the mercy of our environment and time spent with friends is a subtle but enriching experience. So get out there and try it, forget the campsite, forget the law, just find yourself a pocket of Britain’s remaining wilderness and enjoy it in all its glory!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
     &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/peakdistrict/album_8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-peak-district</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-peak-district</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going Ultralight: Refining the Essential</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having taken preliminary action in the &lt;a href=&quot;/features/going-ultralight-1&quot;&gt;first article&lt;/a&gt; we have established a decent starting point for an ultralight base weight.  Depending on the quality and cost of your existing gear you should have a current base weight somewhere close to mine, perhaps even lighter.  From here there is still a surprising amount of weight to be saved just by customising what we have already.  In this installment I will be making small weight reductions in several places, retaining all of the functionality and spending very little indeed. Scissors are an ultralighter’s best friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up, water; there are some easy reductions to be made here simply by switching to retail plastic water bottles.  The hiker’s favorite brand seems to be Smart Water at the moment due to the fact that the thread of the bottle top matches perfectly with Sawyer filtration products, and the slim design makes it easier to fit them into free space in your pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight2/watercontainers.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supermarket water bottles make for cheap ultralight alternatives to aluminium and heavier plastic camping equipment.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find any 1L bottles so I bought 3 600ml bottles for 60p each; sans the plastic ring and label they come in at 30g each, I’ll upgrade to two 2L bottles when I can find them.  I added a 7g scoop because it makes filling the bottles in a stream much easier, really reducing the chance of cross-contamination.  These bottles are cheaper than my existing water containers and save me a total of &lt;strong&gt;98g&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next easy saving can be made with my cooking system; while my Trangia 28-T is fantastic, the burner makes up two thirds of the overall weight and I hardly ever use the frying pan.  I did a quick bit of research into homemade soda can stoves and after some deliberation settled on the [Yak Small] stove design from Logan Watts at Bikepacking.com. This stove features roughly the same burn time and a faster time to boil as the Trangia but weighs 90% less. I got straight into it with my scissors and after a few cuts and scrapes ended up with a 10g stove which not only replaces the 115g Trangia stove, but also functions as its own pot stand. Weight saved: &lt;strong&gt;258g&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight2/cookset.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;At only 360g the cute Trangia mini is already light but being able to leave nearly 3/4 of it behind is even better.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reduction in overall carried weight means that I can afford to have a more flimsy, lighter backpack with less padding and structure.  By reaching for the scissors once again and mercilessly attacking the straps which are now surplus to requirements, I can make the final easy weight saving move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first to go are the adjustment straps for the waist belt and the extra length on the shoulder strap adjustors which I only use when carrying enormous weight.  Next I removed the extra elastic attachment points which I have never used and took the heavy aluminium frame from the main compartment. 
If my pack weight continues to drop, removing more adjustment straps and even the waist strap will become an option. Chopping up my pack saved me a total of &lt;strong&gt;245g&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight2/pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The lighter your pack contents, the fewer comfort measures your pack needs, the more enjoyable your hike; a cascade of happiness!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve spent a grand total of £2.40 and saved &lt;strong&gt;601g / 1lb 5.2oz&lt;/strong&gt;. Now I have refined the essential components of my ultralight set up, I am going to add a small bag of toiletries and quality of life improvers which I think are well worth the weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sawn off toothbrush and a small tube of toothpaste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunblock&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alcohol gel and toilet paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tiny but useful microfibre towel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total weight: &lt;strong&gt;171g&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight2/complete.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My beginner ultralight pack.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This completes the basic set up and turns it into something I think provides the maximum comfort for the smallest weight.  The best part is that even brand new this whole system will only set you back about £120; a great intro to ultralight backpacking and a perfect way to start microadventuring or taking longer overnight trips with little to no impact on your wallet or legs! My  beginner ultralight pack for a total of &lt;strong&gt;3913g / 8lb 10.0oz&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the ultralight pack is complete you might think that everything is sorted, but there is still quite a lot to think about if you are serious about carrying the bare minimum.  I will continue the journey to true ultralight camping in part 3: Worn items and food.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/going-ultralight-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/going-ultralight-2</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Lake District: Wild Camping and Black Sail</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Black Sail is a pretty special youth hostel. It has a reputation as one of the most inaccessible youth hostels in the UK. Based in the heart of the Lake District, it is only accessible by either a six mile trek up the valley from Ennerdale (not the TV show) or by mountain pass. However, just because it’s remote, that doesn’t mean it isn’t popular. The hostel is closed over the colder months (November thru to March) and has just 16 beds (eight male and eight female), which means that the weekends over the popular summer season get booked up fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We managed to bag four beds on a Sunday night in May by booking the previous October and then decided to plan a slightly bigger trip around that booking. The Lake District does not legally permit wild camping but it is tolerated as long as some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lakedistrict.gov.uk/visiting/where-to-stay/wild-camping&quot;&gt;quite reasonable rules&lt;/a&gt; are followed. After driving up from Hertfordshire on the Friday we stopped off at The Twa Dogs in Keswick to plan a route and general wild camping spots for the Friday and Saturday nights, taking us to Black Sail on Sunday night and back to the car on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/1-planning.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Totally non-staged route planning photo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time was not on our side on Friday night (&lt;em&gt;just one beer never means just one beer&lt;/em&gt;), we picked out potential camping spots on the OS map. We rocked up to a candidate spot in the black of night, considered it suitable, pitched up and hit the hay. Late night wild campers can’t be choosers. When the sun rose, and the rain settled in, we were greeted with a proper view of our site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/2-morning.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Good morning wood&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After packing up, we made a swift visit to Keswick to pick up supplies, grab some brekkie and then we were ready to start our trip proper. Black Sail is conveniently placed within (reasonable) walking distance to England’s tallest mountain, Scafell Pike. With that in mind, our route on Saturday took us into the belly of the Lake District, allowing us to tackle Scafell Pike and finish the walk to Black Sail throughout Sunday. We parked the car in Stonethwaite, the start of our circular route, and set off through Langsrath Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/3-blea.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Blea[k] Rock&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture a round of the popular British TV quiz show, QI (I’m picturing it before Sandi Toksvig, when Stephen Fry was still presenting). A stock photo of the Lake District pops up behind our guests (let’s go for Daniel Radcliffe sitting next to Alan Davies, with David Mitchell and Ulrika Jonsson on the opposite side). Stephen forms a question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now, moving on to our glorious national parks. It is well known that the Lake District is ironically home to taller peaks than any located in the Peak District. The Lake District, of course, contains England’s tallest mountain, Scafell Pike. The choice of name for the Peak District is better understood by the number of peaks located in the Peak District, 108 of which are over the height of 245m. However, do you know how many lakes there are in the Lake District?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan chirps up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I went on a family holiday to the Lake District when I was 11. My resounding memories from the trip were rain and me and my sister arguing about who would be the dog in Monopoly for the fifth game in a row.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Light audience snicker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David interjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve got a very old version of Monopoly in our household. So old in fact that all the original playing pieces have all long gone missing. So when you’re picking your piece, that means you have a choice of: a green army man, a large black button, a tiny comb, a fridge magnet of the letter “C”, a thimble (but not the one from the original version) and a laminated picture of Alan Titchmarsh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience guffaws&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan, ever the fool, goes for the contrary answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I bet there’s some stupid meaning for what a “lake” is; I’m going for zero”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SIRENS WAIL&lt;/em&gt; The screen flashes “0”, “0”, “0”. Alan rolls his eyes and Stephen smiles from ear to ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Not quite Alan, anyone else?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel gives it a shot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I haven’t been to the Lake District but my family does have a version of Monopoly with my face on the board. That’s just one item from the many in my Mum’s weirdly obsessive Harry Potter memorabilia collection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conscientious audience laughter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Complete stab in the dark for this one, I’m going for 52”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen smiles once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Looks like your natural wizarding talent didn’t help you out. Any more for any more?”. Ulrika stares blankly and Stephen continues. “Well, Alan nearly had this one”, the screen behind changes to a picture of Bassenthwaite Lake, “There is only one lake in our district of lakes. Whilst there are many bodies of water within the Lake District, it is only Bassenthwaite Lake, close to Keswick which has “lake” in its title. However, there are 16 other bodies of water which are considered to be the main “lakes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All guests roll their eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/4-angle.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clouds part for a short rest at Angle Tarn (not a lake)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a morning of rain, the clouds part as we made our way up to Bow Fell. Still, it was a short reprise; as we reached the last stretch to the peak we were greeted by a mighty wind which cut through to your core. I think the name of its sister mountain, Crinkle Crags, pretty aptly describes the type of rocks right at the top of Bow Fell. The well trodden path towards the peak of Bow Fell disappears 20 metres before the summit and becomes a crinkly craggy scramble (or difficult to traverse interbeds of andesite outcropping from the ground).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/5-bowfell.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from atop Bow Fell&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Bow Fell we descended into the South-Western valley, the area which we’d decided to hunt for a suitable camping spot. At the base of the valley runs Lingcove Beck, a beautiful river which hides new pools and waterfalls around every twist and turn. We located a fine flat piece of grass right next to the picturesque glen at Throstle Garth. A mere two minutes after  we’d dropped our bags on the ground we stripped down to our pants, scrambled down the rocks and had a (very) brief dip in our private pool. If you’re into canyoning, wild swimming or just getting cold and wet; I would heartily recommend this stretch of water to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/6-camping.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Overlooking our camping spot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this trip I brought with me a long held but never used camping accessory, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00FA2RLX2/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00FA2RLX2&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=bolgoe-21&amp;amp;linkId=2482677efd77bd804fcd499be81d1241&quot;&gt;Sawyer Mini water filtration system&lt;/a&gt;. After using it to continually replenish all four of our water supplies throughout the trip, I cannot understate what a fantastic piece of kit this is. This 60g filter uses a fibre membrane to filter out 99.99999% of bacteria. Without getting too technical, the force of the flow sends water through hundreds of U shaped micro tubes; these micro tubes have tiny 0.1 micron pores which capture and stop any bacteria, allowing only clean water to pass. We sat by the stream in the morning and filled up 10 litres of water in about 10 minutes. It most certainly beats relying on water purification tablets; the water comes out crystal clear and has a crisp, clean taste to it (which, in hindsight, is probably more a property of the water from the Lake District springs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/7-water.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Replenishing water supplies with the Sawyer filtration system&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday morning we began our ascent towards Scafell Pike. After getting stuck knee deep in mud during my &lt;a href=&quot;/features/wild-camping-dartmoor&quot;&gt;previous solo trip to Dartmoor&lt;/a&gt;, I was wary of the telltale signs of a bog when crossing Great Moss to the base of Scafell Pike. With patient caution we navigated our way through and surveyed our route up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/8-ascent.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Contemplating the ascent of Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring Scafell Pike is another peak, Scafell. Which, from many angles, including the southerly route we approached from, appears taller than Scafell Pike. Whilst Scafell Pike is regularly traversed by coach-led tourists, Scafell is a popular draw for climbers. UKC (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukclimbing.com/articles/page.php?id=2853&quot;&gt;UKClimbing.com&lt;/a&gt; calls Scafell “England’s finest cliff” with a “sublime climbing experience that is second to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/9-spooky.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;2spooky4me&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we reached the top of Scafell Pike we stopped for lunch, making sure to take all our rubbish with us. Why do I mention this? Well, much like our favourite celebrities, there is often a cruel price that must be paid for fame. Wasdale Mountain Rescue Team has a long history of posting scathing statuses on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/WasdaleMRT/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; relating to the state of England’s tallest peak: “Shocking amounts of litter, people creating new paths, the stink of urine and worse on the summit of Scafell Pike this morning”. They also posed the question of whether a climb to the peak was the highlight of the day, or a trip to the tip. I can’t really attest to seeing a huge amount of rubbish, well, except for a Liverpool FC flag which someone had attached to the summit marker…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/10-celebration.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Slight premature celebration on Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading back down the north side of the hill we were met with breathtaking views of Great Gable (claim to fame at 9th tallest mountain in England) and the surrounding scenery. This valley leads all the way to Wasdale Head, the most common place to embark on the climb to Scafell Pike; therefore, there is a pub. The Wasdale Head Inn has great home-fry style chips but to its discredit, it does not serve &lt;em&gt;Scafell Pint&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/11-greatgable.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View down to Great Gable just off Scafell Pike&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Wasdale Head we embarked on the final stretch of the day, Black Sail Pass. Tired, and legs heavy we were delighted to see Black Sail Youth Hostel nestled in the side of the hill as we descended into the valley of River Liza. We were met by the welcoming James who checked us in, cooked us dinner and sold us wine. Key tip if you’re staying at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yha.org.uk/hostel/black-sail&quot;&gt;Black Sail&lt;/a&gt;, bring cash! The central area in Black Sail has tables and benches which surround a roaring wood-burning stove. Placards on the walls also answer the age old riddle: what came first? Black Sail or Black Sail Pass? You’ll have to go yourself to find out the answer out to that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/12-blacksail.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Last stretch to Black Sail&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning we were cooked breakfast and given packed lunches (I promise this wasn’t a school trip). We donned full waterproof gear, having been extremely lucky with the weather up to that point, and headed towards Honister Pass. The final stretch back to the car took us along the road through Seatoller where we paused, you know, just because we like standing around in the rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/13-wet.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;W e t b o y e s&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completing our circular route at Stonethwaite we found a conveniently placed bus stop to change out of our wet things; all of us experiencing the familiar feeling of satisfied tiredness that comes from getting lost in nature for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/blacksail/14-dry.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dry&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/black-sail</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/black-sail</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 Hours in the Wicklow Mountains</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick dash to Dublin on the plane and an hour’s drive south will bring you to the Wicklow mountains. I set off on a friday night after work, sunk a few pints of Guinness, hiked all day Saturday, and was back in time for Sunday dinner. Here’s a few of the pictures I took during my time in these fine hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/1-lugnaquilla.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ascending Lugnaquilla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wicklow mountains make up the largest expanse of moors and uplands in Ireland, its highest point is Lugnaquilla standing at 925m, which although tall still falls short of those in County Kerry. It takes just over an hour to drive out from Dublin to the base of Lugnaquilla, if you take the scenic route, which will reward you with views of vast bleak moors for sure, on a good day views of the Irish Sea, and if you keep your eyes peeled, the odd christmas tree dressed up with tinsel and baubles - no I’m not joking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/2-cloghernagh.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nice looking cairn at the summit of Cloghernagh&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just a few hours of walking we were treated with sun, bitter wind, sleet, hail, and rain. Fortunately we were prepared and didn’t suffer too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/3-summit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The top of Lugnaquilla, the tallest mountain in the Wicklow’s, standing at 925m&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit of Lugnaquilla, which translates to ‘hollow of the wood’, consists of a wide plateau. The ascent is mostly very gentle and we were surprised at how quickly we summited the mountain. There are steep faces on either side named ‘north prison’ and ‘south prison’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/4-nicespot.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;I’d quite like to move here&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a circular route which began in Glenmalur where there is a car park just south of the Glenmlure Hostel. The ascent begins on a wide forestry road but quickly turns into an easy scramble up 100 metre or so, which really was the only the challenging section of the walk, but certainly nothing to worry about. From then it’s just a matter of keeping on the path and not getting caught out but sphagnum bogs - &lt;a href=&quot;/features/wild-camping-dartmoor&quot;&gt;something Harvey learned a lot about in Dartmoor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/5-ireland.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Just one of the many beautiful spots Ireland treated us to&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the summit of Lugnaquilla we descended via Cloghernagh, the location of the cairn pictured earlier. From there it’s an easy descent back down to the road and walk back to the car park. The whole hike took us about 5 hours, which was taking at a gentle pace and the total length is roughly 10 miles, making this an easy hike that more or less anyone could enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/6-weather.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Approaching inclement weather&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some more pics from my trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/wicklow/album-6.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-wicklow</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-wicklow</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OS Maps App Review</title>
        <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;price&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free from App store and Google Play &lt;br /&gt;
1 month subscription: £3.99&lt;br /&gt;
1 year subscription: £23.99&lt;br /&gt;
Or use redeem code from a paper map to download an area&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurate route planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offline downloads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPS location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drains battery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the incredible progress of the digital world in the past decade many outdoor enthusiasts and adventurers still find themselves reaching for a paper map before setting out for an adventure. We’re lucky in the UK to have fantastic maps in the form of Ordnance Survey 1:25k and 1:50k. They are a joy to use due to their accuracy and excellent design. Of course there have been great strides in mapping technology such as those made by GPS, however, devices are still expensive and not an option for everyone. That’s where the OS maps app steps in, offering digital versions of our favourite maps from our phones, a device most people already possess, offering a cheap way to access the accuracy and solace afforded by a GPS device. We were excited at the prospect but how well does it work? A part of me thought that it must be too good to be true. We’ve been using the app for the last few months and here’s what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has several types of map available to use for different purposes including the standard 1:25k and 1:50 OS maps as well as as  typical road map for use in the car, plus another for when driving at night. It also offer satellite imagery as well as an ‘offroad routing’ map which is a simplified style, not dissimilar from the Google/Apple/Bing map style, but with contours and paths shown in National Park areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be noted that you will not be able to access 25k and 50k maps without either using a redeem code found in all new OS landranger and explorer maps to download an area, or by paying a subscription, giving access to nationwide mapping, either monthly or annually. You can then save these maps for offline use as and when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also plot routes for either running, walking, or cycling, which you can save and share if you like. The app will show how long your route is, elevation data, and provide an estimated time needed to complete the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-use&quot;&gt;In Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time I’ve been using the app I have found it to be very reliable and useful. The practicalities of being able to quickly glance at a phone beats stopping to unfold a map, particularly in windy conditions. I have found the GPS location to be very accurate even when far away from mobile service. Obviously you need to be wary about the safety of your device, most mobile devices are still vulnerable to damage whilst being used in adverse conditions. I use a Quadlock phone case with a rain cover which I would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/1-title.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/2-options.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/3-derwent1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/4-derwent2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/5-route.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/osapp/6-sharing.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highly recommend this app. It functions very well and is reliable when you need it to be, although I would still recommend using it in addition to a physical map and compass, rather than solely relying on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating: 4/4&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/os-app-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/os-app-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
