<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BOLDLY GOES</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 13:32:12 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 13:32:12 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kielder Observatory and Skyspace</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/kielder/sunset.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries Northumberland was a land of wild lawlessness, be it from the times of the Roman Empire when Hadrian’s wall marked the edge of civilisation, keeping the rebellious Picts at bay, or from the days of the Scottish Marches, when Reivers raided the lands, running protections rackets called ‘mál’s’, leading us to the modern word Blackmail. Indeed, Northumberland, the northernmost part of England, has throughout history been a bleak and dangerous place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/rocks.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I stood next to the Hadrian’s wall, high up on the edge of Walltown Crags, on a cloudless day, it was hard to imagine Northumberland’s turbulent past. Indeed, today it is a place for tourists to leisurely admire. And come to think of it, it’s also place of many superlatives: it is, afterall, home to the largest forest, the darkest skies, and the sparsest population in England and Wales. Yet it is the least visited of our national parks. For all of its rugged history and vast swaths of hills, forests, and moorland, the National park seems to have passed most of us by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/portrait.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that piqued my interest in visiting the park was its status as an International Dark Space: it offers the best views of the night skies in England and has the largest area of protected night skies in Europe. I am certainly no more than a casual astronomer at best and have never really seen an unpolluted night sky. So I jumped at the chance to visit. Here are some more pictures from my trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/observatory.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The winning design: created by Charles Barclay architects of London, chosen from from 230 design entries&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/telescopes.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The small telescopes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/hall.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; The Skyspace is an echoic subterranean hall with an apertured ceiling for viewing the sky with the naked eye&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/kielder/car.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/kielder-observatory</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/kielder-observatory</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alpkit Compact Ultra Twins Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great Value for Money&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small pack size&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Quick release locking mechanism&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Nordic style handle not to everyone’s taste&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small and fiddly hand strap&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Not always practical for tarp camping&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compact ultra is a collapsible pole that folds down to a very short 38cm, making it very packable and particularly convenient for plane travel, trail running or climbing. The pole is assembled by slotting the sections together, much like a tent pole, and then pulling one end to put tension into an internal cable that is then locked in place by snap lock. You can then adjust the top half of the pole to your desired length and secure with the single quick release locking mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/collapsed.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handle is a Nordic style design with a non detachable velcro hand strap. It is worth noting for those who may not have encountered this style of grip that you cannot use the pole with your hand on top of the handle, like a walking stick, as the size and shape of the grip makes this uncomfortable. Likewise, it’s worth pointing out that while the hand strap is well made and looks really nice donning its Alpkit logo, it is rather small and fiddly making it hard to put on quickly. I found this design fine for long flattish walks where I could consistently hold the poles for long stretches of time but rather annoying on more technical hikes where I wanted to take my hand out of the straps often and quickly. If you plan to wear gloves in conjunction with these poles you may find it difficult to fit your hand in the strap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to point out with this design is that while its collapsed length is very short, its minimum erected length is rather long (insert cock gag here) making it not particularly versatile for tarp camping where you may need shorter pole for your setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the relatively tiny £34 price tag of these poles there’s question that quality you can expect would be lower than more expensive and familiar alternative options from the likes of Leki or Black Diamond. What you can expect here is a very compact folding pole that mostly bears the hallmarks of a product at its price but with a couple of nice features added in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hand strap, albeit small, is nicely made and I found it quite comfortable. I would prefer if it had a quick release clip or was simply larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/strap.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal cable that runs down the centre of the pole is protected by a fairly thin plastic sheath. I noticed that when the pole is collapsed this cable is pulled tight against the edges of the pole segments, right now mine are holding strong but I will keep an eye on them as it looks vulnerable to damage, and if the cable breaks the pole become useless, something you wouldn’t want to happen on any long hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this price, finding a branded alternative is quite difficult particularly one of this style with similar features. For instance any Leki pole that collapses as small as this will certainly cost more than £100, and the cheapest trekking pole they sell is still £5 more than the Alpkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/compacttwins/fullpole.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need a pole that packs particularly small and you are on a budget, this is an excellent option. You can for the price, expect to forgo some practicalities and some quality, but ultimately Alpkit has succeeded here in filling a space in the market for an imaginatively designed product delivered at an unbeatable price. I would have rated this product 3/4 if the handle and strap where just a little better and easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-24&quot;&gt;Rating 2/4&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/compact-ultra-twins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/compact-ultra-twins</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Borough Bivvy Bagging</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s 4.30 in the morning. I’m in a beautiful nature reserve in the London borough of Barking and Dagenham, in what should be very peaceful surroundings for sleeping out beneath the night sky. However, reality at this time was not quite that serene and rather than being snug in my bivvy bag and sound asleep, I found myself up a tree instead. Oh the joy and adventure of the great outdoors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/hammersmith.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Hammersmith and Fulham&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it all began…I’ve been a fan of sleeping outdoors for quite some time now. Laying there beneath a canvas of stars, with nothing but a couple of layers of material and my face exposed to that deep dark blue night sky, with a cool sweet breeze upon my face. My idea of bliss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to do all my wild camping in tents; it was great fun and cheaper than staying in hostels and b&amp;amp;bs but then I discovered the bivouac. This was at the break of Spring in 2014, and I haven’t looked back since that first undertaking. I developed such a bug for it that I have now slept outdoors without a tent 132 times (not that I’m counting or anything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My passion is for long distance walking which consists of a linear route that lasts 5 to 10 days. During these trips a bivvy at the end of the day can be very rewarding and usually guarantees a good night’s sleep. It’s always good to escape the city for a while, leaving all that mayhem behind and allowing yourself to reset. Obviously living and working in London means I can’t always get away when I want, so a couple of years ago I thought why not bring the adventure to my doorstep and try bivvying in London itself. At that time I thought this was surely a terrible idea and probably not possible but one late august evening I decided to give it a go; venturing out with a friend to Hackney Downs to attempt our first bivvies in London. I went into this thinking of all the things that could go wrong; the sheer population of London, the state of some of its’ green spaces, and a general fear of the unknown. Upon waking up in the morning I was pleasantly surprised to find I had had an undisturbed sleep and possibly one of my best bivvys to date which ended with watching a beautiful sunrise over a sleepy East London skyline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/hackney.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The first one, London Borough of Hackney&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience gave birth to really experimenting with what is on my doorstep and led to a 30 night challenge of sleeping outdoors in London for the whole of September. Each evening I bivvied at a different location and also woke up in some of London’s famous green spots in the likes of Hyde Park, St James Park and Hampstead Heath. It was a truly eye opening challenge and gave me an immense appreciation of just how green London is and the richness it has to offer in terms of open space. Places right here at home, where you can still achieve a calm and peace, completely clearing your head and recharging your soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/westminster.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;St. James&#39; Park, London Borough of Westminster&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing this eventful experiment I was hungry for more and decided that I would walk the London Loop; a 150 mile circular route around Greater London, very much like the M25, but which acts as a green corridor around the city instead. I wanted to do this during my working week so decided to undertake it as a number of night rambles ending with a bivvy in whichever area I found myself in. It took 12 nights in total during the winter season and even saw me go on a date with my now girlfriend (we were third date in). It took me to areas of London that were completely unknown to me; such as Barnet, Hounslow, and Bexley which was another wonderful insight into how much there really is to play with and escape to within the Capital. As well as this, I realised that  the landscape of these green spaces in the city are so varied as I have been able to hammock as well as bivvy in woodland, marshes, fields and even a cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/sutton.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Sutton&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’ve always liked collecting things; whether it be postcards, football stickers, or national park bucket lists, I think they’re important fragments of what makes up our individual identity. Having worked out I’d slept outdoors in 23 of the 32 London Boroughs, I realised my latest collection would have to be bivouacking in all of the boroughs and so was born my idea of  ‘borough bivvy bagging’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/greenwich.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Greenwich&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so back to why I found myself up a tree on a Thursday night in the middle of Dagenham. I had had a solid sleep until I was awoken at 4.30 in the morning to the vibration of thuds not too far in the distance. Trying to get back off to sleep was put on hold, as they got closer, and seemed to have multiplied. Low and behold, it was only a band of wild horses that had landed at my little camp area. For the next 15 minutes it was a game of figuring out each others intentions and evidently freaking each other out, which resulted with me seeking higher ground and climbing up the nearest tree. My actions were odd enough to send them packing to the other side of the stream from which they had come and for me to slowly make my way back down to my bivvy bag with a little less pride than the beginning of the night. I lay back laughing remembering how each bivvy in London has been unique whilst witnessing another beautiful city sunrise. That was another borough bagged and ticked off the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/barking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;London Borough of Barking and Dagenham (with the infamous tree)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be moving out of London in 6 weeks time and relocating to the Peak District. I’m cutting it slightly fine but I fully intend on completing the challenge before I leave.  What Brent, Ealing, Croydon and the other remaining 3 will offer I don’t know. But I do believe that every little corner of London has some form of space to get lost and rediscover yourself in by escaping and enjoying the simplicity of sleeping under the stars. It hasn’t let me down so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/challenge-map.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Progress so far on my London Borough challenge map&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 down, 6 to go! And surely I need to complete the challenge with a final bivvy in the City of London (technically not a Borough) as a kind of icing on the cake. That or finally get moved on by the authorities or picked up by the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/borough/haringey.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;With friends, London Borough of Haringey&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer of making the most of what’s on offer right in front of you, and achieving a sense of thrill and excitement by working with what you have and turning restrictions into opportunities. It’ll be an odd mantel but one that will live with me forever. So thanks for having me London.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/borough-bivvy-bagging</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/borough-bivvy-bagging</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aplkit Hunka Bivvy Bag Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great waterproofing&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Well made&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Light&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Recent price hike&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Not very windproof&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Hunka from Alpkit.com for £35 in May 2016 after seeing it recommended on Alastair Humphreys’ website.  360g seemed very appealing for overnighters when compared to my tent at the time which weighed 1.4kg, but it has proven reliable enough to be a fixture of my overnght kit even now I own a 680g tent.  If you want to get close to nature, the thin but reliable Hunka is as close as you can get while staying dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/length.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;At 215cm x 80cm the Hunka just about accommodates my normal length sleeping bag. Anyone over 6&#39;1&quot; will want to upgrade to the Hunka XL.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alpkit listed the Hunka’s country of origin as China on their website so when I saw the price, even when I took the reviews into account, I expected lacking build quality and materials.  As soon as I opened the package I could feel the ripstop nylon was smooth and almost luxurious, all my fears faded and have stayed in hiding as the product has made it through it’s first year not just intact, but like new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hems and joints show no sign of weakness on the Hunka, they are mostly stitched twice and have been finished well, I found no loose threads anywhere on mine.  Inside, the seams are taped very securely and almost invisibly; I have packed, scrunched and folded my Hunka hundreds of times and they show no sign of budging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/stitching.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;All of the seams are rock solid, the tape on the inside isn&#39;t going anywhere either.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawcord and clasp at the opening and on the footbox net feel slightly plasticy and stuck a little to begin with, but now I have worn them in they function smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been rudley woken up by a trickle of cold rainwater in the night previously I can tell you that the main feature to look for in a bivi bag is waterproofing, and on paper the Hunka is no slouch, boasting a 10,000mm hydrostatic head and a “2.5 layer design”.  These decent stats come without substantial weight and have kept quite a few showers and many more heavy dews away from the Hunkas warm, dry, precious contents (me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/waterproof.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Even after being pushed about in my pack for a year, the waterproofing still hasn&#39;t faded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 3 season standard length and width Vango sleeping bag fits snugly in the Hunka with just enough fabric left to shield my face from rain.  The key to that perfect fit is the tapered profile which seems to have been thought out well and eliminates excess fabric and therefore excess weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slightly grippy inner surface of the Hunka coupled with the tailored style means that your sleeping bag and the Hunka move as one. This secure fit makes maneuvering back on to your sleeping pad in the night much less difficult and minimises the chance that your sleep-fidgeting will lead to a tangle, which means no freezing rain water spilling into your sleeping bag during the night as you sleep.  The tight fit will be an issue for bigger people or anyone hoping to use an inflatable sleeping pad and quilt, the Hunka XL which is slightly longer and wider will probably be the better choice there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hunka/packed.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Although it packs down to a nice size in its incorporated stuff sack, it&#39;s much more useful as a dry bag or pack liner.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integral stuff sack on the footbox is a fantastic idea but the awkward ball shape formed by stuffing the Hunka into itself is actually inefficient to pack.  While ball mode is handy for long term storage, I usually use it as a dry bag for my clothes or tech while I’m hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British army Gore-Tex bivi bag is the closest real competitor in terms of price, at £30-40 on eBay it’s a steal, but then again at 800g it’s also a bit of a monster.  Gore-Tex, while definitely more windproof than the Hunka and probably more resistant to rips and tears definitely won’t pack down as neatly and is a noticeable weight in your backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bivi bag most frequently recommended to me has been the Snugpak special forces bivi, which looks similar to the Hunka but is constructed from Paratex and features a zip (why?!).  While is has been reviewed well and even comes recommended by Ray Mears, the extra weight and £75 price tag make choosing it over the Hunka unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there the prices only get more painful; with options like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/equipment-c3/tents-shelters-c25/bivi-bags-c41/survival-zone-lite-ultralight-bivi-bag-p120&quot;&gt;Rab Survival Zone or Survival Zone Light&lt;/a&gt; you get a 100g weight saving but you’re also chancing it with that 1,000mm hydrostatic head, and breaking the bank on the £110 price tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimal design of the Hunka overall is worth praise; there don’t need to be any grand designs with a bivi bag; it just needs to be light and waterproof, and that’s what you get here.  There are two drawcords which work well and the rest of the focus is on the vital part; the waterproof but breathable shell, all packed into a 360g package for less than £50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating 4/4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the price has sadly risen to £47 recently, the Hunka is still the best choice for anyone not ascending Everest.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/hunka-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/hunka-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>48 Hours: Wild Camping in Dartmoor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On the days approaching the Easter bank holiday weekend I knew I wanted to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; but could not settle on where to go or what to do. Fellow BoldlyGoer James suggested a few places but it was Dartmoor that really grabbed my attention. It is the only area in England where rights for wild camping are enshrined in the &lt;em&gt;National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act&lt;/em&gt;. Whilst not all of Dartmoor is covered by this, there are some pretty sizeable areas which allow wild camping (if you’re curious, have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0007/43909/vi-camping_map_309.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; map created by Dartmoor National Parks). After researching them on my 1:25k OS map for Dartmoor (OL28) I began to think about how my trip may go down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan unfolds in my mind… Drive down to Dartmoor on the Thursday, park up, hike and wild camp on the Thursday evening followed by a full day of walking on the Friday, wild camp that night and then hike back to the car on Saturday and drive back home. That’s about 48 hours. I decided that was short enough to carry all the supplies, food and water I would need for that time on my back, in my newly acquired &lt;em&gt;Osprey Atmos AG 65&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/1-pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pack, car and pack mule&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, due to the inevitable crash which always snarls up the M25 leading up to a bank holiday weekend I arrived in my planned starting point of Harford at about 7pm, a little later than planned. With sundown at around 8pm I made haste up into the hills to find a suitable spot to set up camp and have some dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/2-road.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Road to Harford&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just in time for sunset I reached Piles Hill and hunted for a flat spot to set up my tent. I thoroughly recommend this area or any of the surrounding hills for breathtaking views of Dartmoor at sunset and sunrise. It’s only about a 30 minute walk from the nearby (free) Harford car park too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/3-cairn.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Piles Hill Cairn&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I’d got the tent set up, the sun was just disappearing from view so I cracked out the gas stove, cooked up a Jamie Oliver &lt;em&gt;squeeze-out-the-bag&lt;/em&gt; dinner and scoffed it down. With darkness slowly crawling over the countryside and no desire to start a campfire, there really wasn’t much else to do but call it an early night and get some rest for a full day of hiking the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that this was my first experience of wild camping on my own. It’s a surreal experience to get used to; every sound outside of the tent amplified, making you question its origin. Even though I did have the internal reassurance that my wild camping pitch was entirely legal, it still didn’t stop me from imagining some wild beast, or worse, fellow camper, waking me in the night… Still, I got some kip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/4-camping.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Camping on Piles Hill (no pun required)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke early and decided to take a stroll, sans pack, to the nearby Ugborough Beacon which has stunning views out to Buckfastleigh and North Dartmoor. On arriving here I realised that this would also have been a fine spot to camp and would have offered a spectacular view of the sunrise, straight from the tent door!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/5-beacon.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Overlooking Ugborough Beacon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After walking back to my temporary abode, I packed up my gear and embarked on my way with the vague aim of striking camp somewhere North of Burrator Reservoir. Dartmoor offers some very decent paths if you stay on the beaten track and most of these run along the crest of the hills meaning that there is very little ascending and descending to be done. Dartmoor generally isn’t too hilly compared to our Lake and Peak District National Parks. The highest point in Dartmoor is High Willhays at 621m, way up in the top left corner; but the hills around the bottom part of Dartmoor are all below 500m. However, if you should stray from the beaten track, you may well be in for a calves aching exercise traversing the common grassy tufts. One of the most familiar sites along my trek were the famously furry, wild Dartmoor ponies; their tracks are littered across every path in Dartmoor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/6-ponies.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dartmoor ponies preparing to drop their seminal rap album&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another regular sight is sheep, their beady eyes staring until they’ve somehow decided you’re no longer a threat. I remember several times where a sheep was happily munching away on some foliage with its back to me when it would hear my footsteps and suddenly fly around to make eye contact. Dude, come on, I mean ewe no harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/7-pits.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Erme Pits (spot the ram)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my walk through Dartmoor I was greeted by a handful of people happily singing hello along with the question that demands to be answered by another question, lest, god forbid, you should strike up conversation…&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
   -   &lt;em&gt;“Hey! How’s it going?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   -   &lt;em&gt;“Hi, you alright?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did get talking to a couple of chaps out for a stroll from Ivybridge who informed me of a famous book about the area, &lt;em&gt;Dartmoor 365&lt;/em&gt; by John Hayward; named as such because there are approximately 365 square miles in Dartmoor. In this book, John details one specific site of interest in each of these square miles. My single serving friends also informed me that there is a lively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/296555273885240/&quot;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/a&gt; of people who go out of their way to photographically document as many of these 365 sites as possible. In my mind this is akin to geo-caching or a treasure hunt. After my excursion to Dartmoor, whilst sitting in the comfort of my own home, I requested entry to the group, was accepted, and proceeded to peruse some of the pictures posted in the group. I can proudly state that I have visited at least one of John Hayward’s 365 points of interest, Ditsworthy Warren, a rather spooky looking abandoned cottage near to Sheepstor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/8-warren.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ditsworthy Warren (totally not haunted)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ditsworthy Warren I headed to Sheepstor, skirting round Burrator Reservoir and up to Sharpitor aiming to find some camping spot with an epic view of the water but not too exposed to the elements. One risk with wild camping is that you’re constantly searching for that goldilocks spot… &lt;em&gt;“maybe the grass is greener on the other side of that hill…”&lt;/em&gt;.  Eventually I managed to convince myself that the spot I’d chosen was just right and made camp for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/9-gorse.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nestled in the Gorse&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After waking early again I planned my route back to the car whilst hearing a light pitter patter of rain on my tent. Ten minutes after setting off, fully kitted out in waterproofs, the light drizzle abated and I happily stuffed them back into my rucksack. At this point I was starting to feel slightly thankful that my supplies and water were dwindling; reducing the weight on my back and making it a less daunting task to tackle some more challenging obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/48dartmoor/10-planks.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When planning my route that morning I selected a circular route avoiding paths I’d already used. Included in this route was a path with an attractive straight section running south from Whiteworks. It was only after getting home, that I discovered that this stretch of land has a famous reputation. The path crosses over Foxtor Mires, a stinking bog, which is believed to be the inspiration for Grimpen Mire in Sir Arthur Conan Doyle’s classic, &lt;em&gt;The Hound of the Baskervilles&lt;/em&gt;. However, when I planned out my route, I didn’t realise its famous reputation. I didn’t even realise it was a bog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/11-mires.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Foxtor Mires&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Sir Arthur Conan Doyle brilliantly articulates the threatening nature of a bog and the truly terrible fate that could befall a man when he describes the demise of the villain, Mr Stapleton, in &lt;em&gt;Hound of the Baskervilles&lt;/em&gt; in his flight across the Grimpen Mire:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“There was no chance of finding footsteps in the mire, for the rising mud oozed swiftly in upon them, but as we at last reached firmer ground beyond the morass we all looked eagerly for them. But no slightest sign of them ever met our eyes. If the earth told a true story, then Stapleton never reached that island of refuge towards which he struggled through the fog upon that last night. Somewhere in the heart of the great Grimpen Mire, down in the foul slime of the huge morass which had sucked him in, this cold and cruel-hearted man is forever buried.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lost the path crossing through Foxtor Mires before the small bridge which takes you over the stream in its centre. I only found it after 20 minutes of wondering around that godforsaken bog trying to find a safe path, twice getting stuck up to my thighs. I think one of the most treacherous things about a bog is that it doesn’t look particularly threatening. A few tips from someone who has sunk in a bog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do a bog hop on the yellow tufts and keep moving, they’re more likely to take your weight, but not for long.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid any bright green mossy areas. This is where you will sink and you will get wet boots and maybe a wet bum.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a walking stick to probe suspicious patches in front.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t cross a bog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/12-bog.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;I smell like bog&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another three hours of walking with wet boots I reached the car, exhausted but satisfied with a couple of days well spent exploring one of our country’s best national parks. Still I was happy to get back into some warm (and dry) clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/48dartmoor/13-done.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Done&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/wild-camping-dartmoor</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/wild-camping-dartmoor</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trangia 28-T Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Inexpensive&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Light pans&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Small form factor&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Heavy burner&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my mini Trangia 28-T for £18 from outdoorgear.co.uk in May 2016.  The neat stacking design, coupled with the low weight and price made the 28 stand out from the crowd straight away.  After dozens of overnighters and a few weekend trips I need to make some changes to save weight, but my cooking experience has been overwhelmingly positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pot, pot stand and frying pan are made from aluminium with the burner constructed from brass and the handle a lightweight alloy.  The aluminium construction means a slight drop in durability over some titanium counterparts, but the reduction in price and similar weight more than makes up for that in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aluminium pot is immediately recognisable as the design as featured in the larger Trangias which have become famous for standing up to all of the bumps and scrapes that occur in outdoor life.  I have seen several trodden on or sat on, bent completely out of shape, before being pushed back into a rough circle and chucked back on the fire.  Having used my mini pot on gas, alcohol and coals, I have no doubt that this smaller Trangia will stand up to the same punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frying pan is aluminium coated with non-stick coating which looks and feels quite fragile.  Trangia provide you with a sheet of thin plastic to protect the coating from the sharp edges of the pot stand and handle stored inside, this hasn’t stopped chipping where the pan clips over the lip of the pot.  Perhaps more of a design flaw than a quality issue, it is rather annoying and now it is chipped it will only get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burner, pot stand and handle are all solidly constructed; the burner and simmer ring fit together in a satisfyingly snug way; the handle, while flimsy, is actually surprisingly resilient and doesn’t buckle even when the pot is full of water; and the pot stand provides a rigid base for stirring and mixing over heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/handle.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Although it doesn&#39;t look like much, the handle is much easier to grip than the one in the Trangia 25 or 27.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first feature that stood out to me was the tiny form factor of the packed 28.  Everything fits neatly inside the systems pot with the frying pan over the top holding all of the components securely in place with room enough for teabags and 4 or 5 porridge packets to spare.  Being able to pick up one 15cm x 6.5cm item and know that you have packed your entire cookset in one go is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slimmed-down 0.8 litre pot of the mini coupled with the same brass burner as a larger Trangia leads to a much improved boil time, in my experience it takes around 6-7 minutes to boil 1 litre of water.  This reduced capacity has also allowed for a slimmer handle design which eliminates the chance of miss-gripping the pot rim and dropping it, which I used to do a lot with the old design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/overview.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some complain about the lack of a handle for the simmer ring, but you can slide it quite easily if you are careful and lift it slightly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only item which hasn’t changed in design from the larger Trangias is the burner itself.  It provides a stable temperature, doesn’t spit at all and the rubber-lined cap stops alcohol leaking through your backpack, but at 115g it makes up more than a third of the total weight.  I am definitely going to swap the burner out for a homemade coke can stove in the near future and probably leave the frying pan at home too which will reduce the weight to ~200g.  But if I’m changing the burner, leaving the pan (and lid) at home, why bother with the rest of it at all? Why not just buy a pot separately and make a stove to begin with? Well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market for alcohol stoves is limited.  It essentially boils down to Trangia burners, designs that look a lot like Trangia design knock offs, or simple stoves made from cans which seem expensive given that you could make them yourself for next to nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go ultralight straight away and have a tight-ish budget, I have only heard good things about  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.storminstovesystems.co.uk/&quot;&gt;stormin stove system&lt;/a&gt; at roughly £20 and 68g.  Paired with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alpkit.com/products/mytipot&quot;&gt;Mytipot&lt;/a&gt; which is £29 and weighs 94g and a homemade can stove you can achieve a system weighing just under 200g for £49.  But hold on, we already had this with the 28 if you leave the frying pan at home and swap out the stove, all for only £24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try a knock off Trangia design &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/NuoYa005-Solid-liquid-Alcohol-Cooking-Backpacking/dp/B00HBMOSJY/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/SZCXTOP-Portable-Alcohol-Aluminium-Backpacking/dp/B01N56JS2T/ref=sr_1_7?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-7&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Tatonka-Stainless-Steel-Alcohol-Burner-x/dp/B000G4XIA4/ref=sr_1_8?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1492541890&amp;amp;sr=8-8&amp;amp;keywords=alcohol+stove&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;.
The ones I have seen weigh up to 100g more than the 28 burner and pot stand, and once you factor in the cost of a pot too they aren’t much cheaper, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, unless you make your own can stove, chicken wire pot stand, tinfoil wind guard and repurpose an aluminium mess tin as your pot, it’s going to be very hard indeed to find a system as light and functional as the 28-T for anywhere near the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/28t/cooking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Whether you need to stop for a quick brew or cook a major meal for one or two, the 28-T can hack it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I opened my bottle of meths for my inaugural meal with the 28 I was struck with flashbacks to my scouting days.  Stuck on the side of a hill in darkness, three people around a Trangia 25, bodies positioned awkwardly in an attempt to shield the flame from the wind, hungry tempers flaring as pasta floating in a litre of water began to simmer lazily after more than 15 minutes of waiting.  I realised I may have made a huge mistake investing in another product from the same designers but a few meals in I realised most of my fears were misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For less money than a single titanium pot you get a complete, convenient, collapsible system.  Most of the components of the system are handy to have around to use on their own; the pot and handle do well on a gas stove, the stand and pot do well on their own with a different burner, the pot alone cooks on an open fire, the handle fits any pot with a lip.  It’s one of those kits that is so versatile at least one piece of it will end creeping its way into your pack wherever you are heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating 4/4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 28 makes for a brilliant starting stove for a new solo backpacker or a decent ultralight option if you swap out the burner, all for less than the price of a single titanium cooking pot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/trangia-28t-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/trangia-28t-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wisport Sparrow 20 Litre Backpack Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Endless versatility&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Durable&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Comfortable with any load&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Expensive for a 20L&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Heavy&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Sparrow from Military1st.co.uk in March 2016 for £60 after seeing it in use on the &lt;em&gt;AlfieAesthetics&lt;/em&gt; outdoor youtube channel.  I have used the Sparrow as a hybrid pack over the past year, loading up the outer straps with everything I need for a microadventure or weekend trip, then once I have made camp, using it as a day pack on short hikes.  Its impeccable build quality, versatile design and comfort have afforded me an enjoyable, more efficient hiking and camping experience with minimal drawbacks.  The standard Wisport 5 year warranty is the cherry the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/backpack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sparrow is made in Poland by Wisport, a Polish military and outdoor equipment company who supply the polish army among others.  This should tell you straight away that their gear, like most military equipment is going to be bomb proof, but that durability comes with a hefty weight cost.  The Sparrow is made from 500D Cordura, a splash resistant and generally tough fabric which will withstand everything but direct assault with a sharp knife.  This Cordura is held rigidly in place by faultless stitching which has remained rock steady through a year of frequent and quite harsh use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The straps, MOLLE webbing and mesh are all secured firmly; clearly intended to endure the tougher aspects of military life which means they are over engineered for civilian use.  The clips and buckles made by ITW Nexus and Duraflex haven’t lost their spring, and although I have been carrying heavy loads almost every time I have used the pack, show no signs of wear or fatigue.  The expansion connection points look quite flimsy at first but I have slung my 1.4kg sleeping bag from them numerous times with no problem at all.  The only quality issue I have had over 12 months is a frayed strap end, this was solved by resealing the end with a lighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/quality.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Rock solid zips, clips and buckles of the Sparrow inspire confidence even in the worst conditions.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;  Heavy loads can be slung under the pack using the flimsy looking but actually sturdy attachment points.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to fault the design of the Sparrow.  This pack is one which comes with all of the bells and whistles; hydration bladder support, clips for every occasion, straps to fasten all manner of sundries, attachment points for extra straps and standardised MOLLE webbing to attach any other military pockets or sheaths to the outside.  The Sparrow offers all of this while remaining comfortable even with all of these expansion options fully laden, and the option to attach a hip belt if it becomes to unwieldy.  It is a pack so versatile and so accommodating that you might end up packing too much for a microadventure even though it has only a ‘20 litre’ capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/straps.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The side straps of the Sparrow are the key feature, allowing you to carry loads which would be totally unrealistic with any other 20 litre pack.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of the Sparrow features two main pockets, one 5 litre front pocket contains a zipped mesh pocket for keys as well as clips for torches and carabiners.  I normally keep my Trangia, fuel and a bit of food in this pocket.  The 15 litre compartment features a flap to hold a hydration bladder and another zipped mesh pocket; after some gear Tetris there’s room enough for two litres of water, two days food and some well folded clothes.  The one issue when the pack is fully laden is waterproofing, while the Cordura does it’s best in the rain, anything more than a light shower will find its way into your precious sleeping socks straight away.  If you attach bulky items to the outside like me, you’ll want to pack a rain cover for a much larger backpack just in case, I chose a 65L which works well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/opening.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clips, flaps and pockets for all your small items; the fully hinged main compartment makes packing the larger pieces of gear easy too.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sparrow is tough to compare to other 20 litre backpacks, and other backpacks in general.  Generally day packs range from 15-25 litres and weigh 150-500 grams, but I can’t fit everything I can get into (or rather, onto) my Sparrow into a 35 litre Vango, let alone anything smaller.  If you want a more convenient day pack while still being able to go on weekend adventures for the same price as the Sparrow, you could get a, 68g &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.outdoorgb.com/p/Sea_to_Summit_20L_Ultra_Sil_Day_Pack/?utm_source=froogle&amp;amp;utm_medium=directory&amp;amp;utm_content=GBR&amp;amp;currency=GBP&amp;amp;country=GBR&amp;amp;SelectedBundle=184805&amp;amp;SelectedItem=687214&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjww7zHBRCToPSj_c_WjZIBEiQAj8il5K9p-2jg2PjfXTlZlzSqjOBCDi22Q0EWZoLt7aR6rAUaAv-k8P8HAQ&quot;&gt;Sea to Summit Ultra-Sil&lt;/a&gt; and a 45-65 litre  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shop-outdoors.co.uk/regatta-survivor-ii-45-litre-rucksack.html?fee=13&amp;amp;fep=15664&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjww7zHBRCToPSj_c_WjZIBEiQAj8il5KoITSfZ9I8zE1HZJY_2TbWFUY_fzQ57N4YKmhYZj9gaAvYA8P8HAQ&quot;&gt;Regatta&lt;/a&gt;.   This very reasonably priced duo will perform the same functions as the Sparrow while saving you about 90% of the weight during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nightgear.co.uk/en-UK/Snugpak-Xocet-35-Backpack/5150465ng.htm?colour=Black&amp;amp;size=One%20Size&quot;&gt;Snugpak Xocet&lt;/a&gt; is the most similar I have seen; most of the same straps and attachment points with the addition of some handy net pockets on the side for water bottles.  At £20 less than the Sparrow, only 30g more and with generally positive reviews, it’s a real contender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisport are currently introducing their Sparrow II range which sees some changes in the design to make it slightly less utilitarian, and brings the weight down by about 200g to 850g.  This makes it a much more appealing day pack option while retaining the majority of its straps and expandability options.  If mine breaks in 4 years after the warranty runs out (which I still see as being unlikely) the Sparrow II, or by then maybe III, will be my first choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t describe the Sparrow as luxurious, so maybe the it isn’t the Rolls Royce of 20 litre backpacks, but is a Range Rover; expensive, durable, heavy and lots storage options.  The designers thought of everything: attachment points, pockets and hydration bag options; expandability to the point that you will throw out all of your other backpacks below 55 litre capacity in disgust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sparrow/usage.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Being able to pack the same amount as with a 50+ litre bag without the bulk makes this my favourite microadventure bag.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the Sparrow is a brilliant challenge - I can fit my basic shelter on the outside, then I can just about fit my food, water and clothes on the inside.  It has inspired me to cut down unnecessary bulk from my setup and affords me a smug feeling when I see others with larger backpacks who have clearly overpacked for a short trip.  It is a bit of a bulky monster when used as a daypack, but when used in place of a 40-55L and separate 20L pack on a weekend adventure, suddenly all of it’s heavy attachments and over-engineered stitching make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rating-34&quot;&gt;Rating 3/4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need a rugged bushcraft, airsoft or hybrid weekend trip backpack, I would heartily recommend the Wisport Sparrow series.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/sparrow-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/sparrow-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alone in the Wilderness by Joseph Knowles</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt; is the memoir of Joseph Knowles, chronicling his 40 day stay in the woods in Maine which he undertook naked save a loincloth, without any survival equipment whatsoever.  An astonishing tale dotted with perilous encounters with bears and wildcats, Knowles breaks up his account with stories from his life and some of his musings on modern living in 1913.  As you continue through the book you might end up wondering whether the book isn’t all it seems to be…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thoughts on the book fluctuated as I began and finished the first third.  I began bewildered and amazed by just how tough Knowles seemed to be, even compared to the most extreme adventurers of that time.  I have read quite a few books from the turn of the century or before by adventurers and outdoorsmen who survived some truly amazing events.  Woolen garments, cast iron equipment, lacking nutrition and very basic or non-existent maps all made for what must have been a pretty hellish experience.  Knowles, though, seems to be a cut above them all; wandering into the forest &lt;em&gt;naked&lt;/em&gt; without so much as a knife with a plan to survive for 40 days, and all on the whim of a bet made in a bar.  That is a daunting task even for the most experienced bushcrafter when alone, it would surely be the test of his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/joseph.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Joseph Knowles photographed as he emerged from the forest, clothed in bear skin. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in the book Knowles writes of his experiences growing up in the forest in Maine near where he enters the woods to begin his task.  While giving no specifics, Knowles hints that some of the techniques he learned from his mother during childhood will help him to not just survive, but thrive in the wilderness during his stay.  His stories about his childhood certainly gave the impression that he has been tempered to endure this sort of test from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
“I didn&#39;t feel the hunger so keenly now, and as I walked along it came into my mind that I had heard that a man could go nine days without eating. Already I had been away from home three days. It would take two more to reach Wilton, which would leave four more before I actually starved to death, I figured.”
   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - Joseph Knowles&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He speaks of and approaches the whole adventure in a casual manner, spending the first few nights without fire, pacing to keep warm and not sleeping at all.  Fashioning shoes and trousers from bark with ease, he seems to find living in the woods as easy as living in a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read on, I did start to wonder whether some of the things he claimed to have done were actually physically possible.  I began to wonder whether even Ray Mears with a full support crew could dig a pit, trap a bear and beat it to death with just a tree limb in the space of four days with no tools.  Knowles continued that he had used his “bow and arrow” to shoot a large number of partridges without much effort at all.  This was when alarm bells really started ringing for me, it would surely take a fortnight if not more for an experienced bowyer to find and knapp flint for tools, make the tools, find suitable wood, fashion a bow, make the twine to string it, prepare the arrow shafts and heads, find feathers and fletch the arrows, let alone hunt and shoot accurately enough to kill a wild animal.  He had done all this on top of making several fires, a lean to shelter, clubbing a bear to death and spear fishing trout in his first two weeks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/moose.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Knowles left drawings and notes in several caches which were visited regularly by park rangers, these were his only contact with the outside world during his stay.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately turned to Google to find some answers and do some research on this bushcrafting superhero.  Sadly, from what I can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bostonmagazine.com/news/article/2013/03/26/naked-joe-knowles-nature-man-woods/&quot;&gt;find on the internet&lt;/a&gt;, it seems Joseph Knowles was at best a serial embellisher, and at worst (more likely) a con man out to make a quick buck, one of many making a dubious claim in a period when daring feats of endurance were all the rage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed reading &lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt;; even though I  learned the true story halfway through.  Knowles’ writing style definitely has that enticing twang of an old man whose tales probably feature fish twice their actual size, and there are some great (heavily inspired by Emerson) quotes and musings on being outdoors.  Ultimately, the unverifiable stories and questionable claims do mean that the story surrounding the inception of the idea and creation and release of the book are more interesting that the book itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
“As I made my way down to the spring early that morning I knew it was Sunday morning, and the thought came to me of how little churches would be needed if everyone knew and understood nature. Nature is, in truth, a religion in herself.”
   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - Joseph Knowles&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely recommend reading the incredible story of Joseph Knowles and the events surrounding the release of the book, but I’d recommend reading a version written by someone other than the man himself.  Really though, the book isn’t a bad read if you are still curious after that, the notes from Knowles’ friend, freelance writer Michael McKeogh, which apparently formed the basis of the story, did result in a well paced and eventful tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is for certain, he could definitely draw well with charcoal, even if it was from the comfort of a well furnished log cabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/alonewild/doe.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alone in the Wilderness&lt;/em&gt; is available for free as an ebook or PDF from &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/aloneinwilderne00knowgoog&quot;&gt;Archive.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/alone-in-the-wilderness</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/alone-in-the-wilderness</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ups and Downs: The 3 Best and Worst Moments of my First Cycle Tour</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I set off on my first long distance cycle tour. Inspired by the books of Al Humphreys and Mark Beaumont and their adventures travelling the world on two wheels, I saved up for a new bike with all the touring trimmings: panniers, a fancy leather saddle, and horribly uncool but ever-practical accessories such as a bell and kickstand. It had been a long time ambition of mine to go on a cycling adventure and it was exciting to finally have the means to pull at wanderlust’s thread and see familiar winding roads unravel before me and set my sights to the elusory horizon and simply go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/standing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cycled from my house in Hertfordshire, about 30 miles north of London and headed towards Edinburgh. I followed and number of Sustrans cycle routes, a network of on and off-road cycle-friendly paths, including Cycle route 1 which took me from Norfolk all the way up the east coast to Scotland. It took me 7 days to cycle 503 miles, averaging ~70 miles per day. It, for me at that time, was a long and epic journey and it came with many highs as well as lows.  Here’s my top 3 best and worst moments from my first cycle tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-3-best-moments-cycling-from-hertfordshire-to-scotland&quot;&gt;My 3 best moments cycling from Hertfordshire to Scotland&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-the-road&quot;&gt;1. On the Road&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my bike out of the shed, hopped on, said goodbye, and set off along familiar streets just as I would for any Sunday jaunt. My wheels buzzed along the hot tarmac as my mind buzzed with excitement in the knowledge that I wasn’t going to loop round on the normal circuit but instead keep going, out of the orbit of home and off on a northerly bearing towards adventure. Something I hadn’t expected but felt from the first crank was that I had already succeeded. I had planned, prepared, and embarked on an adventure that would have been easy to put off or postpone; to procrastinate from doing at each opportunity. Leaving the house that sunny morning I knew that for better or worse, through whatever challenges came in my way, it would now be easier now to face them head-on and keep going than it would be to accept defeat and turn around and come home. I had finally achieved a long-term goal of going on a long distance cycle tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/upanddown/farm.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unexpected-sights&quot;&gt;2. Unexpected Sights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By travelling by bike or on foot we choose to see the world go by at a slower pace. You get to see lots of things that you perhaps might not expect, the mundanity of journeying becomes the adventure itself bringing you to unexpected destinations that you would have otherwise missed. On my journey I heard accents change every day, subtle changes in geography and fauna, and noticed unique idiosyncrasies, such an unprecedented number of burnt mattresses in Middlesbrough or flags in Lincolnshire. Some of my favourite unexpected sights include a great string of kites in the shape of various creatures in Dunbar, and noticing these birdhouses along a rural road in Scotland. I also saved a Barn Owl that was trapped in a wire fence and met a Dutch septuagenarian who had ridden all the way from the Orkney Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/dutch.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/bike.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/lane.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/box7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/kites.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/gallery/vista.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scotland-is-cool&quot;&gt;3. Scotland is Cool&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I was most looking forward to on my trip was reaching Scotland and its relaxed camping rules that allow you to more or less wild camp anywhere. My first night beyond the border took me to a small village by the name of Foulden. Perched on the brow of a gently sloping hill, the houses of Foulden line just one side of the road, the other side saved from buildings allowing for stunning views across the Tweed Valley all the way to the distant Cheviot hills of Northumberland. I popped my tent up right there on the village green in full view of the houses. No hiding for me that night, skulking out of sight in fear of being shooed off by angry farmers. I was enjoying my right to camp freely in Scotland greatly, indeed, the next morning I was greeted by a friendly local who made me a cup of tea and filled my water bottles before I set off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/foulden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-3-worst-moments&quot;&gt;My 3 worst moments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;near-miss-with-a-nutter&quot;&gt;1. Near-miss with a Nutter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journey ended in the Scottish capital of Edinburgh, once described as a ‘mad god’s dream,’ its windy streets are lined with stone-faced tenements which can in a single moment look every bit as grand as they look austere. Built on seven hills, a qualifying foundation for many great cities, Edinburgh is centred upon a great central rock which perched upon it is a pretty sweet looking castle. I had ridden 500 miles by this time and feeling very happy to be riding through the city to my finish line, but just when I thought I had safely made it, I had a was very nearly knocked off my bike by a car cutting dangerously close in front of me. I slapped the car (classic mistake) to signal that I was there and protest his poor driving. A very angry man got out the car, shouting and swearing at me and seemingly looking for some good ol’ timey fisticuffs.  In this moment my internal fight or flight mechanism slammed down on the escape button and my legs started pedalling furiously. As I made my dash for safety I heard the car revving loudly behind me, I could see in my mirror huffs of black smoke rising from the car as it teared towards me. I bunny hopped off the road and veered off into a park and essentially hid like an idiot from a man who looked like he had murder in his eyes. That was it, I finished the ride, a little shaky but ok. In every other respect Edinburgh treated me very well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/edinburgh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;falling-off-my-bike-in-the-rain-in-hull&quot;&gt;2. Falling off my bike in the Rain in Hull&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I really need I say more? Falling off your bike is a wholly unpleasant experience at the best of times, but doing it after 40 miles of cycling in the rain, with 30 still to go only add insult to injury. It was a subtle ridge on a busy road that derailed me in the city of Hull, a place that’s most famous artwork is a picture of a dead seagull called ‘Dead Bod’ painted on a rusty shed as a joke over 50 years ago, an artwork that helped win Hull the status of Britain’s City of Culture 2017, an award that backhandedly compliments cities that aren’t London every 4 years. I scuffed my hands and knees badly and tore my shorts. I let out an involuntary but hammy yawp in front of a large audiences of drivers and pedestrians, some of which very kindly got from their cars to check I was ok. I thanked them but reassured them I was alright as I cowered off to clean my wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/bod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-perfect-storm-of-bullshit&quot;&gt;3. A Perfect Storm of Bullshit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absolute lowest moment for me came in the form of sheer exhaustion. Having ridden over 70 miles I had just another 10 to go before reaching the campsite that I had phoned earlier that day to book a spot. Last check in was 9pm, they said, any later than that and I’d be wild camping. My cycle route signalled me off the road and onto a rough looking farm track, I peeled off in good faith and kept going until I reached a hill with a gradient that only the most sinewy of cyclists could reasonably attempt. My pannier laden packhorse and my tired (and distinctly undefined) legs took one look and opted to push. Up I went, conscious of my deadline of 9pm closing in. And up and up. Glad to finally reach the top I hopped back on the bike only to ride 50 yards before blowing out a tire. It was 8:30 and I had just five miles to go but in this moment I felt so defeated I could have cried. Mustering up my last remaining scraps of mental fortitude, I got to work fixing the puncture. A quick fix and I was again on my way. Only, my road I had one more challenge in store for me. The last 2 miles of trail were finished with fist size rocks, fine for a fat bike of burly mountain bike but my spindly road tires struggled. I made it, thankfully, just in time but it really is hard to put into words how much it took out of me to get there. I pitched my tent and wandered to the pub for some much needed R+R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/rocks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/upanddown/scotland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/ups-and-downs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/ups-and-downs</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scarpa Delta GTX Activ Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Quality materials and assembly&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Reduced or non-existent wearing in period&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Tough but responsive sole&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Leather isn’t for everyone&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought these Scarpas in early spring 2016, for around £180 from GoOutdoors (from a physical shop for once!) and as far as I can see, they are the tough boots from the idiom. So far I’ve covered around 500 miles in them; wading through streams, walking over hills, climbing up mountains, stomping through snow, slogging through mud, and they have yet to let so much as a drop of water in. All the while they’ve provided a high level of comfort which I didn’t have to earn with a prolonged wearing in period, they fit comfortably right out of the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Drawn in by the leather look and instantly comfortable fit, my Deltas have only improved with age.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the boot is covered in a 2.4-2.6mm leather, with a calf leather upper and tongue joint.  Although a little stiff to begin with (as leather always is) creases wore in straight away at the ankle bend, providing that tailored fit that I have only ever experienced with leather boots.  They have picked up a few cosmetic bramble scratches over the last year, while these haven’t even come close to affecting the boots performance, they have left me a little self conscious about further damage in a way I probably wouldn’t feel wearing boots with a synthetic construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stitching, glue and general construction is all fantastic quality from what I have seen in the last 12 months, nothing has budged even a little bit.  The sole has hardly aged at all, its deep tread still as effective as day one, and even the inner sole is in good condition; still springy albeit missing some surface colour from wear.  The comfort level has only increased as I have worn them in, there have been no weak links when it comes to build and material quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/quality.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A year and several hundred miles in, all of the joints and stitches show no signs of shifting.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compliment the great quality, Scarpa have realised a fantastic design to boot. They are a great mix of old and new boot style; comfortable, traditional calf and cow leather with hi-tech comfort inside and a Gore-tex waterproof lining, all topped off with a springy, bomb-proof, plastic sole. Having worn my pair in deep snow and at the height of summer without dampness creeping in and all sweat creeping out, I can say that the waterproofing and breathability of the Delta is fantastic.  The laces will stay put all day even without a lace locking mechanism and although it’s quite tricky to get the tongue to stay in place to begin with, once you have worn them enough to mould the leather into place, lacing them up is a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sole is springy and manages to feel surprisingly responsive for what is quite a large chunk of plastic, even with the very sturdy toe protector at the front. I’ve felt thoroughly connected to the earth in them almost all the time, these boots are definitely built to make you feel like Godzilla crashing down a hill, rather than a highly tuned and nimble hill walker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/design.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The memory foam, insole and springy sole work harmoniously to provide a comfort level which hasn&#39;t faded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boots have what Scarpa calls “ActivFit”, which means Scarpa made the boot using a special ‘last’ which is the analogue for a human foot used to mould the inner padding. These hi-tech lasts apparently allow for a softer padding to be used inside the boot, and this abundance of soft cushioning is what makes the boots feel better than others right out of the box. The boots also feature a breathable memory foam innersole, which really doesn’t let you down when you find yourself standing for long periods of time eating lunch or waiting for others on the trail. Without knowing about any of these features at the time, I thought they felt better than all of the other boots I tried straight away and I have only had one incident with blisters, so apparently it all works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct competitors in the 3 season leather boot range include the Mammut Brecon II, which costs ~£170 and the heavier Meindl Bhutan MFS, which costs ~£180.  Reading reviews of the competition, I am not instilled with confidence the way I was approaching Scarpa; build quality issues aren’t what you want to hear when investing in something you want to last up to 5 years.  There were actually several user reviews that included lines such as “&lt;a href=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/scarpa-review.jpg&quot;&gt;never gonna last 10 years like my old Scarpas&lt;/a&gt;”, far reaching brand reputation for quality is always a good sign.  From what I have seen, the alternative with the most to offer comes from the British company Anatom, their Braeriach 3 season boot costs only £144 and has been reviewed positively so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/worn.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a regular oil and wax I can see these boots lasting me at least another 5 years,  if they remain this comfortable I’d be happy to wear them all that time too. Insulative, grippy, comfortable and visually pleasing; they tick all the right boxes and support you in all the right places.  I’ve recently seen them online as low as £160, so while not exactly a bargain, they are still very good value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-34&quot;&gt;Rating 3/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely recommend them and would buy another pair in a heartbeat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/delta-gtx-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/delta-gtx-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
